<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation vnto the gouernours, and people of Hir Maiesties countrie of Wales, to labour earnestly, to haue the preaching of the Gospell planted among them. There is in the ende something that was not in the former impression..</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19605.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94666</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572908</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572908</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181007</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00537)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181007)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2153:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation vnto the gouernours, and people of Hir Maiesties countrie of Wales, to labour earnestly, to haue the preaching of the Gospell planted among them. There is in the ende something that was not in the former impression..</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
                  <author>Waldegrave, Robert, 1554-1604, printer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Waldegrave],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Aldermanbury? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Iohn Penri.</note>
                  <note>Place and publisher from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181007:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181007:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An exhortation vnto the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and people of hir Maieſties <hi>countrie of Wales, to labour earneſtly,</hi> to haue the preaching of <hi>the Goſpell planted</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>There is in the ende ſomething <hi>that was not in the former</hi> impreſſion.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 137.5, 6.</bibl>
               <p>If I ſhall forget thee, O Ieruſalem, let my right hande forget her ſelfe, if I do not remember, thee, let my toong cleaue vnto the roofe of my mouth: yea, if I prefer not Ieruſalem vnto my cheefe ioye.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. COR. 1.13.</bibl>
               <p>For wee write no other thing vnto you, than that you reade, or that you acknowledge, and I truſt you ſhal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vnto the ende.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 COR. 5.13, 14.</bibl>
               <p>For, whether we be out of our wit, we are it vnto God, or whether wee be in our right mind, wee are it vnto you. For, that loue of Chriſt doth conſtraine vs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb facs="tcp:181007:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181007:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> Lorde Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of VVales, &amp;c. The reſt of the gouernours there, and to all, the gentlemen, Miniſters and people my my brethren, the inhabitants of Wales: in this life, the true knowledge of a ſauing God, the true feeling of ſin, the full aſſurance of their ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt, wroght by the woord Preached, with outward proſperitie, if the Lorde thinke it good to them, and in the life to come, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting bleſſedneſſe in the kingdome of heauen, I wiſh from my ſoule.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow many and dangerous (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and beloued in the Lord) are the waies, whereby Sathan in this perilous &amp; prophane age wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we liue, carrieth hedlong into hell the moſt part, euen of thoſe amongſt whome, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Idolatrie, and the falſe worſhippe of the true, or falſe God, hath beene abolliſhed; it cannot bee hidden or obſcure vnto any, that vouchſaueth but with a careleſſe eie to conſider, the deſolate bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes of GOD his Church, euen there where it might haue bene moſt fruitfull. And of all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions whereby the Lord in his<note n="a" place="margin">1. The. 2.11</note> iuſt iudgement, hath giuen him power, to be forcible in the hearts of men, none hath bene found more powerful and auaileable then the perſwaſion, that the eternall God requireth no more at the handes of reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, (the creatures) framed according to his own Image.<note n="b" place="margin">Colloſ. 3.10. Gen. 1.26 &amp; 5.1. 1. Cor. 117.</note> Then to exempt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues out of the number, of the out ragious and ſhameles Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or at the moſt, to haue ſome outwarde forme of his worſhip, whereby they might bee diſcerned from heathen and prophane Atheiſts; and ſo hope eternallie to bee ſaued, though they ſhould neuer come where the ordinary meanes of ſaluation (the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181007:3"/>word preached) doth grow.<note n="a." place="margin">Cor. 1.21. Rom. 10.14. Iames. 1.21. Ephe. 1.13.</note> Now, I would to God that among the reſt of the nations vnder heauen, this latter perſwaſion had not taken fearefull hold vpon you my brethren the people of VVales. For how haue you liued now full 29. yeares, in al which time vnder her Maieſties proſperous raigne, you haue not embrued your hands with profeſſed Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry? haue you not for the moſt part, in reſpect of the publicke ſeruice of God, contented your ſelues with leſſe then publike reading? and in the meane time, do you not thinke that the Lorde, in regard of the knowledge of his wil, &amp; the outward practiſe thereof, the obſeruations of his Sabboths, the right vſe of hys Sacraments, the full aſſuraunce of your owne ſaluation; requireth no more at your hands? And which is moſt wofull, though you now liue in this palpable and groſſe darkenes: yet verie few or none among you, conſider this your caſe, to be the verie condition of thoſe, who ſhall neuer ſee Ieſus Chriſt in his kingdome to their comforte, but the meere eſtate, of ſuch as ſhall receiue their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce in hell ſier, with the deuill and his Aungels, euen moſt intollerable and bitter tormentes for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer. From which reprobate and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate of wofull damnation, neither man nor angel can ſhew, how the whole country of VVales, or anye part thereof may bee deliuered, vnleſſe it ſhall pleaſe God to worke in the heartes of all men there liuing, acording vnto their ſeuerall callings, and eſpeciallie in yours, (right Honorable) and the reſt in publicke authoritie, or ſupplying the place of eccleſiaſticall gouernours, a conſcience, to haue the woorde of reconciliation, planted among you and your people. VVhich if you the magiſtrates, &amp; gentlemen, ſhall neglect to bring to paſſe, you the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181007:3"/>Biſhops and Miniſters not regarde to perfourme, you priuate men, as a thing not belonging vnto you, ſhall contemne: then be you aſſured, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you perſuade your ſelues to the contrary, that on the fearful &amp; diſmal day of iudgement, both the one and the other of you ſhalbe iudged vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting woe and deſtruction, for the offence which conteineth in it theſe two ſinnes. Firſt the wilfull contempt of that holie ordinance, by which alone the Lorde hath appointed to conuey ſaluation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, the refuſall of eternal bleſſednes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentlie, the deſperate renouncing of Ieſus Chriſt, and his precious merrits. Secondly, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious reiecting of thoſe markes, whereby in the ſight of Gods children and the world, you might be knowne to bee of the number of the Lords choſen, not one wherof (beſide your great contempt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt I ſay, for you may haue the word preached, if you woulde earneſtlie ſeeke the ſame for ought you knowe) you leaue vndone, if you refuſe to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe any paines, troubles, or charges, to haue the bleſſed Goſpell of the almightie God procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among you.</p>
            <p>And firſt in regard of God his ordinance, knowe this, and know it to practiſe, that if you hence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as hitherto you haue doone, preſume to liue wythout the preaching of the worde, you do by wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wicked rebellion tranſgreſſe that decree, whereby the Lorde of his infinite and vnſpeakable wiſedome hath ordained, to bring menne vnto his kingdome. The contrarie whereof, if any dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, then the holy ghoſt demaundeth what the Lorde Ieſus the glorious wiſedome of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meant, when<note n="(1)" place="margin">1</note> he<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.8.1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12.13.</note> ordained paſtors and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to continue in his church, for the gathering
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181007:4"/>togither of the ſaints, the worke of the miniſterie, the edification of the body of Chriſt, euen (2) vntill wee all meete togither,<note place="margin">2</note> in the vnitie of faith, and knowledge of the Sonne of God, vnto a perfit man, vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulnes of Chriſt. Woulde any of you blotte himſelfe out of the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of thoſe that are ſaints? Woulde anie of you diſmember himſelfe from our head Chriſt Ieſus? I hope not: then, as ſure as God liueth, you can not be priuiledged from continuing vnder thoſe, whom the Lorde hath appointed for that worke, vntil ſuch time as you be growen vnto that meſure of faith &amp; knowledge, wherevnto nothing may be added. (3) Can you be made ſaints?<note place="margin">3</note> Can you bee made mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt? (which you muſt needes be)<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Cor, 10. 2. Epheſ. 1.1. &amp; 4.7. 1. Cor. 5.16. Act. 20.23. Reue. 22.15.</note> or elſe you can haue no inheritance among (4) them that are ſanctified, but bee excluded out of the citie of God, amongſt dogges, theeues, murderers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters, if you be not wrought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their hands, whom the Lord hath ſanctified to that office? I am bolde therefore in the cauſe of Gods honour, and of your own ſaluation to intreat you,<note place="margin">4</note> as you meane to haue anie fellowſhip and communion in heauen with the bleſſed ſaints and angels, as you intend to haue anie part in that kingdome, which the Lorde Ieſus hath purchaſed with his owne bloud, as you woulde haue any intereſt in him, and his ſacred paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that while you haue time, you labour with might and maine, to prouide your ſelues of the meanes whereby you may bee tranſlated out of the kingdome of darknes, wherin you now liue, vnto the bleſſed poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſweet Sion, the citie of the liuing God. In which cauſe, if your endeuours wil be colde and backeward, I pronounce vnto you, that you ſhal as ſurelie periſh, and bee damned, as the Turkes,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181007:4"/>Heathens, or any other Idolaters, who cannot abide the name of Ieſus Chriſt. Be afraide therefore, as the apoſtle<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 4.1.</note> admoniſheth you, leaſt by forſaking the oportunitie of being ſaued, which at this day is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto you, you be depriued of your ſaluation. How ſhal you be able to beare it, when in the day of vengeance, you ſhall ſee your ſelues arraigned of high treaſon before Gods tribunall ſeate, for reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the pardon he offreth in Chriſt Ieſus vnto you? Would you but vouchſafe to ſeeke the ſame in the worde preached? In the worde preached, I ſaye, for if you will imbrace Chriſt, and haue pardon of your ſinnes by his paſſions, you muſt haue that brought to paſſe by preaching. Chriſt, I graunt, may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe taught, but as the apoſtle ſaith,<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 4.21</note> not as the truth is in Ieſus, and therefore wythout comforte, and wythout ſaluation. The ſmall reckoning, my brethren, that hitherto you haue made of Chriſt truely taught vnto you, teſtifieth vnto your faces, that you haue not knowen the Lord,<note n="c" place="margin">Iere. 4.22.</note> that you are fooliſh children, wiſe you may be to doe euill, but to do well you haue no knowledge, as ſaith the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Yea, it teſtifieth, that you declare your ſinnes, as Sodome, and hide them not, and out of al doubt it will bring woe vnto your ſoules,<note n="d" place="margin">Eſay. 3.9.</note> vnleſſe you haue preaching, for you haue rewarded euill vnto your ſelues. For Chriſt his ſake, then for your owne feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eities ſake, acknowledge in the practiſe of your liues, that the Lorde hath tied (5) the foode of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and knowledge vnto the mouthes of thoſe paſtors,<note place="margin">5</note>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 3.15.</note> who at the (6) leaſt in regard of gifts,<note place="margin">6</note> are according vnto his owne heart.<note place="margin">7</note> The Apoſtle proclaimeth (7) vnto the Coloſſians,<note n="f" place="margin">Golloſ. 1.20.21.</note> that as it was the good will, pleaſure, and decree of the eternal, to reconcile all men vnto himſelfe by Ieſus Chriſt: ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181007:5"/>he neuer purpoſed to make this reconciliation kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto any, but by the word preached:<note n="a" place="margin">verſ. 23.28.</note> he telleth (8)<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 16.25. 1. Tim. 3.16. 1. Cor. 2.7.</note> vs in many place,<note place="margin">8</note> that ſaluation is a myſtery, &amp; ſo of neceſſitie muſt haue ſome wider opening, than the withered hands of bare readers can reach vnto. (9) Bleſſed Peter ſheweth in plaine wordes, that our newe birth can no way be wrought in vs,<note place="margin">9</note> but by the worde preached.<note n="c" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.21</note> Thoſe great and (10) hidden ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes, which the very Prophets themſelues coulde not attaine vnto wythout greate inquirie,<note place="margin">10</note>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.10</note> can be made knowen vnto you, belike contrarie vnto the expreſſe word of the holie ghoſt,<note n="e" place="margin">voiſ. 12.</note> by thoſe who can not preach the Goſpell.<note place="margin">11</note> In what (11) a deſperate caſe then is my deare country, the place of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres of my fathers,<note n="f" place="margin">Nehe. 1.</note> who hopeth for ſaluation, and hath no meanes to be brought into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth,<note n="g" place="margin">1. Tim. 24.</note> by the publike miniſterie? And what a publike miniſcerie, or miſerie rather is that, in whoſe handes ſaluation is not, becauſe the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, is not in their handes? Ieroboam, (12) woulde thou haddeſt againe thy vnlearned prieſts:<note place="margin">12</note>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2. Chro. 13 9</note> For it is out of controuerſie, that they are ſit to be the miniſters onelie of them that woulde haue no God,<note n="i" place="margin">2. Cro. 15.3.</note> but we would haue Ichouah for our God,<note place="margin">13</note> and ſerue him. Timotheus (13) to the ende he might be made more fit to cal men to ſaluation, was commaunded to take heede vnto himſelfe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to learning, and to continue therein:<note n="k" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.13 15, 16</note> but our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, if they can reade, are able without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learning to make ſaluation knowen vnto vs. Is reading (14) the way whereby the Lord will beſtow vpon men the ſpirite of wiſedome,<note place="margin">14</note> and reuelation thorough his knowledge?<note n="l" place="margin">Ephe. 2.17.</note> No, no, (15) downe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto hell with that doctrine whence it ſprang,<note place="margin">15</note> and iſſued, that ſeeketh ſaluation vnto men by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181007:5"/>of that which canner be vnderſtoode, without an expounder.<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 8.30.32.</note> And here I would (16) know of you, which ſo long haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented your ſelues with bare reading,<note place="margin">16</note> whether for the ſpace of nine and twenty years complet, you haue ſelt, either in your ſelues, or perceiued in others, the woorde to haue bene ſo powerfull as it is ſaid to be,<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> If you haue not, bee you aſſured, that it is not the worde whereof the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh in that place, which worketh thoſe effectes in ſome of the hearers, either vnto death, or vnto life. For the word of God is liuelie, as hee there ſetteth downe, and mightie in operation; and ſharper then anie two edged ſwoord, and entereth through, euen to the deuiding aſunder of the ſoul, and the ſpirit, and of the ioynts, and the marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and the intents of the heart. Beſides, that wofull experience ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the ſpirite of God, meaneth not the word read in this place, the ſecond verſe of the chapter, euidentlie conuinceth, that it muſt needes bee the woorde preached, vnto whome theſe imperiall ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles (as I may ſay) are aſcribed. But ſaye the holie ghoſt what it will ſay: the people of Wales, had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be lims of the deuil, to bee euerlaſtinglie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, then labour to haue the woorde, that by meanes thereof, they might be made the members of Chriſt, and ſo eternallie ſaued.<note place="margin">17</note> Though (17) the or dinaunce of God be to demde the worde aright,<note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> vnto the ſeuerall vſe of the hearers, though (18) ſaluation be a thing that muſt be learned,<note place="margin">18</note> euen of them who can read:<note n="d" place="margin">Coloſ. 15.7.</note> our reading Baalites, ſcane able to reade,<note place="margin">19</note> (19) though the decleration of the ſame, bee ſuch a thing as euerie chriſtian who can read well and diſtinctlie, is not able to perfourme,<note place="margin">20</note>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim 5.22. epheſ. 4.7.12.</note> (20) and ſuch a thing as proceedeth not from and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181007:6"/>gift of nature in vs,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12.3.77. ephe. 3.8. 1. cor: 3.21.3.10, he. 6.4.</note> reading a naturall gift, (21) though it be a labour to be ouer anie people in the Lord,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9. theſ 5.12. tim. 5.17.</note> a labour, (2) ſo woonderfull, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the admiration thereof, crieth out, who is ſit for theſe things?<note place="margin">21</note>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16.</note> Reading a worke of ſmall labour and leſſe wonder: yet you my deare countri-men, wil rather aduenture the bloud of your ſelues,<note place="margin">22</note> (cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and frozen ſecuritie) than giue eare vnto that great ſaluation, whiche firſte was preached by the Lord himſelfe,<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 2.3. ephe. 2.17.</note> and can be made or dinarily know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en vnto no nation vnder heauen, but by (23) prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> How can the way of ſaluation (24) be made known vnto you by thoſe that are not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall?<note place="margin">23</note>
               <note place="margin">24</note>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.13.</note> O Lord, haſt thou euer giuen them (25) anie allowance to bee thy Miniſters,<note place="margin">25</note> whoſe lippes neuer preſerued know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> and dare wee gaine-ſay thee to thy face in admitting them,<note place="margin">26</note> furious madnes (26) to thinke that our readers according to the Cannon of the word, haue the meſſage of ſaluation in their hands, whereas they haue no more fitnes to declare the ſame, in regard of ſufficiencie, than a verie Painim, Turke, or Iewe, which denieth and defieth Chriſt Ieſus, may well inough haue, if hee can read Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh or welch? A thing to bee aſtonied at, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the worſhippers of heathen gods, that the religion of chriſtians, and the woorſhip of the God that made heauen &amp; earth, ſhould not haue in it ſo much as one miſterie, (27) whoſe ſecrecie, euen in regarde of knowledge,<note place="margin">27</note> might diſable one that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of true religion, to be a publike Miniſter thereof. O earth couer this our ſinne: O heauen conceale it, leaſt in the wrath and anger of God, hell requite it. What wordes ſhall I vſe to make this ſincke deeplye into your Honours heart; and into
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181007:6"/>the hearts of others whome it concerneth, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that the great God, the mightie and fearefull Lord, hath a great and a blouddie reckoning wyth England and Wales, and the gouernours of them, (28) becauſe the of-ſcouring of all contempt,<note place="margin">28</note> and deriſion, are permitted to repreſent his place, and perſon among vs. As ſure as the Lord liueth, thys ſinne ſhall neuer bee vn puniſhed, vnleſſe betimes you repent, &amp; betimes redres this ſacrilege, by pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thoſe ouer vs, who may truly ſay of themſelues; Nowe then are wee ambaſſadours for Chriſte, as though God did beſeech you through vs, wee pray you in Chriſt his ſtead, that you be reconciled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> He ought not (29) to be a miniſter, that hath not this commiſſion,<note place="margin">29</note> yea and dooth not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully excecute the ſame, whatſoeuer vngodly men babble tot he contrarye. The reaſon whiche out of their darke and diueliſh vnderſtanding, they haue framed for the confirmation of their errour, which is, that the Apoſtles indeede were commaunded to preach the goſpell, but our miniſters are to do no more then read, that which they preached ſhall be vouchſafed, a large confutation when my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reaſons, wherof I haue inſerted aboue of ſcore, to prooue that our readers bee no miniſters, are anſwered. In the mean time, I vſe theſe arguments againſt this leprous error.<note place="margin">30</note> Firſt (30) the baſeſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique readers ought to haue more in them then<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 4.6. deut. 6.7. Pſal. 78.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> parentes, bothe vnder the lawe and the Goſpell, who though ſimple, and vnlearned, yet hadde the burthen of teaching others, laid vppon them, not by reading, for it may be they could not do it, and a ſauage Caniball that coulde reade, might well i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough inſtruct others, in that which coulde bee made knowen by reading. And wil our curats reiect
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181007:7"/>it?<note place="margin">31</note> Secondly, (31) reading is not that wholeſome doctrine, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.</note> which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery miniſter is bound to deliuer vnto the hearers: prooued bicauſe there was neuer anye profeſſing religion in any age, who could not well abide the word red, ſo that there were nothing gathered out of the ſame, contrarie to their iudgements or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, wheras the apoſtle ſaith, it ſhould come to paſſe, that men would not abide the wholſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſpoken of in that place. I diſdaine to refell the obiection that the apoſtle ſhould meane either the olde heretiques, who denied ſome part of the word, or the antichriſtian Papiſts, who forbad the word to be read vnto the people in a vulgar toong. Thirdly, (32) all men in what age ſoeuer they liue, haue as much need of teaching,<note place="margin">32</note> as they who liued in the apoſtles time, bicauſe all are borne citizens of the kingdome of darknes, &amp; cannot be brought into the kingdome of Chriſt by any other inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than the<note n="b" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.13.23</note> worde preached. And the roote of (33) corruption euen in the regenerate,<note place="margin">33</note> bringeth foorth buds like it ſelfe, which muſt bee cut off by the worde preached. I doe not denie, nay, I know it is warranted, that the worde ſhoulde be read in the congregations of Gods children,<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 13.15.17. Nehem. 8.2.</note> but that hee ſhould be taken as a publike miniſter that hath no other gift, that I deteſt, that I abhorre: becauſe I knowe the Lorde accounteth it for no better than ſwines bloud, the cutting off of a dogges head, the bleſſing of an idoll, or the killing of a man, in his ſight<note n="d" place="margin">Iſay 66.3.</note>, Laſtly, the worde read, is the (34) ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all,<note place="margin">34</note> whereas the foode of eternall life muſt bee made milke vnto the weake and tender, and ſtrong meate vnto them which are capable thereof.</p>
            <p>But woe is mee, be the worde read as groſſe as it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181007:7"/>may be, my country men (lamentable and wofull deluſion) thinke it inough for them, to ſwallow that which containeth in it the food of the ſoule, though in their ſtomacks it ſhould turne into ſtarke iron. A few pſalmes,<note n="(35)" place="margin">35</note> a few praiers, with one chapter of the newe Teſtament in Welch (for the olde neuer ſpake Welch in our daies, though, to my comfort, I vnderſtande it is all readie to be printed) moſt piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully euill read of the reader, and not vnderſtoode of one among tenne of the hearers, is that meanes belike whereby the Lorde hath decreed to make cleare vnto all men, in Wales, what the fellowſhip is of the myſterie,<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.9.</note> which from the beginning of the world hath bin had in God. Theſe be the onlie viſions that our prophets haue tolde vs of, for the moſt part. Oh that the Prophet Ieremie, or ſome man indued with his ſpirit were now liuing, to raiſe vp that complaint of vs, and our countrie, which he tooke againſt Ieruſalem, and the people of his dais?<note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 2.13, 14.36</note> What thing ſhall take to witneſſe for thee? What ſhall I compare to thee,<note n="(36)" place="margin">36</note> O'daughter Ieruſalem? What ſhall I liken to thee that I may comfort thee, O virgine, daughter Sion? For thy breach is greate like the ſea: who can heale thee? Thy prophets haue looked out vaine and fooliſh things for thee, they haue not diſcouered thine iniquitie to turne awaie thy captiuitie, but haue loked out for thee burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome prophecies, and cauſes of baniſhment? Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I know not howe our ſtate might better be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphered. For the wordes of the Lorde are founde true in vs, if euer in anie people, the leaders of my people cauſe them to erre, and they that are led by them are deceiued, and queſtionleſſe, it may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſaide of vs,<note n="c" place="margin">Ierem. 5.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> my people delight therein.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as men liuing without the worde
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181007:8"/>preached, thinke themſelues in a tollerable eſtate before the Lord, I woulde know<note n="(37)" place="margin">37</note> whether they may hope for eternall life, which profeſſe not the true religion in that ſorte alone, as the Lord would haue the ſame profeſſed: the anſwere will be, they cannot. Againe, I would knowe, whether there be anie more true religions, that is, waies to ſerue God aright, and ſo to come by ſaluation, than one: it will be anſwered, no. And concerning ſaluation, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that there neither is, nor hath bene, any more waies, ſince the beginning of the worlde, but Chriſt alone, as it is ſet downe in expreſſe wordes:<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 15.6.</note> I am the waie, the truth, and the life, no man commeth to the father, but by me. Neither is there ſaluation in anie other, for among menne there is giuen no name vnder Heauen, whereby wee muſt be ſaued, but ouelie the name of<note n="b" place="margin">Actes 4.12.</note> Chriſt Ieſus, as Peter teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieth. I demaund alſo whether this way, both for the ſubſtance and manner of Gods ſeruice, be not ſet downe in the worde of God alone, and not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to be founde? It will not be denied, I trowe; I am ſure it cannot. For if either the ſubſtance, or maner of God, ſerurce ſwarue from the Lordes will reuealed in his worde, who knoweth whether it be allowable in his ſight or no? And therfore who wil aduenture to offer it vnto him? Theſe things being thus ſet downe, I affirme, that this one onely true religion<note n="(38)" place="margin">38</note> was neuer publikelie profeſſed, this one onelie way to ſaluation, neuer ordinarilie attained vnto ſince the beginning of the world vnto this day, but by the word preached. And it will neuer bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe while the worlde ſtandeth. Enquire now of the daies of heauen that are paſt, which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, ſince the day that Adam fell from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, demand from the one end of the heauen
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181007:8"/>vnto the other, and all with one conſent will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that from Adam vnto Noach, from Noach to Moſes, from Moſes vnto Ieſus Chriſt, from his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed appearing in the fleſh, vnto this preſent houre, no face of a true church apparant, without prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, no ordinarie ſaluation wythout preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and this decree ſhall neuer bee<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 3.15. iud. 14. gene. 4.26. &amp; 5.22. hebr. 11.5, 6. 2. pet. 2.5. heb. 11, 12. 1. pet. 3.19 20. geneſ. 9.27. compared with 11.10. &amp; 14.18. hebr. 7.1.8. gala. 3.8.6.9. rom. 4.3. hebrews. 11. the whole chapiter, gene. 45.6. &amp; 12.12. &amp; 17.9. &amp; 18, 19. hebr. 12.17. geneſs. 48, 49, the two whole cha. &amp; 50.24, 25. exo. 3.7. actes. 7.20. hebr. 11.23. iob. 33.23.24. deute. 33.9.10. mala. 2.5.7. nehem. 8.4.8. hezra. 7.2.5. hebr. 4.2. pſa. 95 7, 8. and 78.5, 6. acts. 15.21. and 3 22. deute. 18.15. heb. 1.1.2. Iud. 1.5.1. 1. cor. 1.21. epheſ. 4.11. rom. 10.14.</note> chaunged. I doe not denie, but that the Lorde may if hee will, ſaue thoſe, who neuer heard, or ſhall heare Sermon in all their liues. But wretches as we are, what is that to vs? Wee haue no warrant to hope for anye ſuch ſaluation. Nay, if anie will preſume, that they may come into heauen, &amp; not ſubmit themſelues vnto the voice of the Preacher, I dare tell them, were they the greateſt potentates vnder Heauen, that they ſhall neuer be ſaued. I woulde to GOD then, my brethren, that as manie of you as liue this day, whereas there is no preaching, coulde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in what an hopeleſſe condition you liue. I know you feele not your own miſery, if you did, you would not continue in it to gain a thouſand worlds.</p>
            <p>Although it woulde be the ioie of my ſoule, to ſee you in the way to heauen, where in now you are not: yet it wil not be the loſſe of a button vnto me, though you ſhoulde all of you go to hell: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoeuer I write, it is doone in good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, of loue and compaſſion towardes your miſerie. Deceiue not your ſelues then, ye are not in the eſtate of ſaluation, hauing neuer enioyed the worde. O you are in hell, labour to come out, in the ſhadow of death, ſeeke for the ſunne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to ſhine vpon you. I will pawne my ſoule, that you are heires of perdition, and ſhall ſurely go to hell, for aught any man knoweth, vnleſſe you bee otherwiſe taught than hitherto you haue bene. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181007:9"/>the diuell himſelfe may as well hope to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as you can, who neuer ſaw the beautie of their feete that bring ſaluation, God will not be mocked at your hands. Are you not reaſonable men? Haue you not ſoules to be ſaued? Woulde you not bee ſhrowded from euerlaſting woe vnder the wings of Ieſus Chriſt? Why then ſtriue you not for the word preached? If the Lord ſhoulde ſummon you at this houre before his iudgement ſeate, haue you anie thing to ſhewe why hee may not proceede againſt you with the ſentence of iuſtice<note n="(39)" place="margin">39</note> in purſuing you with his eternall curſſe, for the breach of his lawe? What will you anſweare for your ſelues, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede you ſhall be arraigned before God and his angelles, for contemning the woorde preached. I ſpeake now vnto the gentlemen &amp; people of Wales, will you pleade, that the fault was not in you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you haue beene deceiued by thoſe, whom the Lorde in his iuſt indgement hath raiſed vp to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the light of his goſpel in this our age, I meane the racke-maiſters and tormenters of Gods bleſſed worde, who laying the ſame vppon the racke, haue conſtrained it to confeſſe what it neuer meant, as either, that reading is preaching, which is ſenſleſſe, or that men may be ſaued without preaching which is diuelliſh? This will not ſerue the turne. Wil you proteſt, that you woulde gladly haue hadde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? It is not ſo. For you neuer as yet opened your mouthes for the ſame. And nowe being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therevnto, it ſhall appeare what little reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you make thereof, by your careleſſe enterpriſes that way. One thing more I will ſay, that for anie meanes you haue to be ſaued in the moſt congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Wales, you ſhall be firebrands of hell. Let the magiſtrates in the meane time ſee how well the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:181007:9"/>Lorde is ſerued vnder their gouernement. See you vnto this, my Lord, or els the curſſe of God wil light vpon you, for your careleſneſſe in this point. Hath the Lord called you to be lorde preſident of Wales vnder her Maieſtie, to the ende, you ſhoulde fit ſtill when you ſee your people runne vnto hell, and the Lord ſo notably diſhonoured vnder your gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The eſtate of Wales not being amended by your meanes, the poore people ſhall die in their ſins, and be damned, but their bloud will the Lord require at your hands. If you ſay, it lieth not in you to build vp our breaches, or that you are otherwiſe emploied, and ſo can not intend this worke: that which a ſeelie olde woman replied vpon Philip king of Macedonie, ſhall be your anſweare. Shee cryed for iuſtice at the kings hande, and that her cauſe might be heard, the king anſwered, that hee was not at leiſure. No? quoth ſhe, then be not my king. So, my Lord, with reuerence be it ſpoken vnto your Honour, if it lie not in you to bring Wales vnto the knowledge of God, or if your leiſure will not ſerue thereto, then bee not the Lorde preſident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>That it eſſentially belongeth vnto your calling, to ſee all within Wales taught by the woorde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, is prooued, by reaſon that you are gouernor ouer all. For you ought to acknowledge your ſelfe ruler ouer none, that doe not ſubiect themſelues at leaſt outwardly vnto true religion: becauſe that all whoſoeuer are vnder anye mannes iuriſdiction, ought to keepe<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 20.10 and 12.48, 49 Numb. 9.19.</note> the Sabboth: ſo that if anie Turke, papiſt, or other pagan idolatour remaine in any our cities or townes, he ought to be compelled to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe to the outward ſeruice of the true God, or expelled. This is ſhewed by the practiſe of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181007:10"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Neh. 13.15.21.40</note> Nehemias. Now it is a cleere caſe, that no people can keepe the Sabboth<note n="(40)" place="margin">40</note> hauing not among them the exerciſes required by the Lorde, to be practized on the Sabboth. And what exerciſes of the Sabboth can there bee there, where the worde preached is wanting. Gouernors my Lorde, muſt gouerne vnder God. They haue no allowance to be rulers, wher the Lord is not ſerued, where he hath no acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuperioritie, there man hath no commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him to beare rule. Satan hath a kingdome my Lord, where Chriſt ruleth not. And dare you be Satans lieuetenant?<note place="margin">Conſider pſalm. 2. &amp; 101.7.8.</note> doe you make no conſcience to be regent, where the ſcepter of chriſts word beareth no ſway? eſpecially not labouring by all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that it may haue the authoritie. It hath pleaſed God to ſende the word into your honours familie. If you would declare vnto the world (which thing you ought to be careful of) that the power of the worde hath touched your verye ſoule, with a conſcience to ſerue your God, you can neuer doe this as long as you haue no care that the Lorde bee glorified in as many as he hath committed vnto your gouerment. You are here diligently to take heede then, leaſt you deceiue your heart in perſwading it of the Lords fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towards you, if he hath not made it carefull to build vp the ruines of Ieruſalem. Hereby alſo all the magiſtrates vnder the ſunne may vnderſtande, that howſoeuer they mainteine the truth of religion, yet they haue flatly denied the power of godlines, vnles they ſeriouſly endeuor to draw their ſubiects out of the ſnares of blindnes and ignorance. They are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to know, that the Lord requireth the very ſame thing at their handes, as a demonſtration of their loue towards him, which he did of<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 21.15.16.</note> Peter. Howbeit, in another manner. Saying, magiſtrates loue you me?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181007:10"/>Then ſee that all the people committed to your charge be fed with knowledge. Magiſtrates loue you me? then traine vp your people in my feare; Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates loue you me? then take heed that I be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honored of your people. The trueth of the things here ſet downe concerning the magiſtrates duetie, being as ſtable as the heauens themſelues, it ſhalbe your H. part to anſwere the Lord no otherwiſe, then by the execution of thoſe thinges which he hath ſo neceſſarily and fatally layde vppon your ſhoulders. Wey them, good my Lord, and let not another yere of your Preſidentſhipp paſſe ouer your head, before Wales of a daughter of wrath, bee made an heire of mercie and fauor, which the Lord graunt.</p>
            <p>I am now to come vnto our Byſhops, and the reſt that ſupplie the place of miniſters in Wales, who in aſmuch as they are the verye ground-worke of this our miſerable confuſion, muſt not thinke much to haue the words of the holy Prophets in times paſt, ſpoken againſt their predeceſſors, the wicked priſts and Leuites, applied vnto them. But in this place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen into this<note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.1.2.</note> iangling and pratling age of the worlde, wherein faith and the power of religion, is thought by the moſt part, to conſiſt onely in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of Byſhops, and withſtanders of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I confeſſe from my heart, that I haue bin hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawne to deale with this wicked generation. Not becauſe I would haue theſe cormorants vntouched, but leſt I ſhould ſeeme to feede the humors of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 14. &amp;. 6.20. 2. Tim. 16.23</note> who increaſing themſelues ſtill vnto more vngodlines, thinke nothing ſo well ſpoken or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as that which is ſatyricall and bitingly done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt L. Byſh. and the reſt of that ſtamp. As I would not nowriſhe this frantike conceit in any, ſo far beit I ſhoulde allowe with my ſilence, the butchers and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181007:11"/>ſtranglers of the ſoules of my deare countrimen. Who if they be not driuen by this warning, to looke better to their charges, I will hereafter ſo decypher their corrupt dealing, that the very ayre it ſelfe ſhal be poyſoned with the contagion of their filthineſſe. They who are not guiltie, or not touched in the ſpeache following.</p>
            <p>Wales is ſaid to be in a tollerable condition, for it hath had many preachers of a long time. The more ſhame then for them, that it hath had no more tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. This I dare affirm and ſtand to; that if a view of all the regiſteries in Wales be taken, the name of that ſhire, that towne, or of that pariſhe, cannot bee found, where for the ſpace of ſix yeres together with in theſe 29. yeeres, a godly &amp; learned miniſter hath executed the dutie of a faithful teacher, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his miniſtery in any meane ſort. And what then ſhould you tell me of Abbey lubbers, who will take no paines though they be able? If I vtter an vntruth, let me bee reprooued, and ſuffer as a ſlanderer, if a trueth, why ſhall I not be allowed? I know very wel, that to ſpeake any thing at all in theſe dayes againſt the Clergie men, is to ſpeake in Bethel with poore<note n="a" place="margin">Amos 7.12.13</note> Amos, to propheſie in the kings court, and ſo to be buſie in matters of ſtate. Miſerable daies; Into what times are we fallen? That theeues and murtherers of ſoules, the very paternes and patrons of all coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, proud, and more then popelike tyrants, the very defacers of Gods trueth, vnlearned dolts, blind guides, vnſeaſonable and vnſauory ſalt, drunkardes, adulterers, foxes and wolues, mire and puddle, to be briefe, the very ſwineſtie of all vncleannes, and the very ignomie and reproche of the ſacred miniſtery, cannot be ſpoken againſt, but this will be ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes made a matter againſt the ſtate. And therfore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181007:11"/>although all the miſerie, all the ignoraunce, all the prophaneneſſe in lyfe and conuerſation, hath beene for the moſt part by meanes of our Biſhops, and our other blinde guides, yet may not a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme ſo much with any ſafety, leaſt he be ſaid to be a mutinous and factious fellowe, and one that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the ſtate.</p>
            <p>For mine owne part, the prophet Malachi ſhall deale with you, and let the reader conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his wordes ought not in a fearful ſort to ſtrike and aſtoniſhe you. A ſonne<note n="a" place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> (ſaith the Prophet) honoureth his father, and a ſeruaunt his maiſter, if then I bee a father,<note n="b" place="margin">Read Mala. 1. &amp; 2. chap.</note> where is mine honour, if a maiſter, where is my feare, ſaith Iehouah of hoſtes vnto you. O ye Biſhops of VVales, that deſpiſe his name? If you ſay, wherein haue we diſpiſed him? it wil be anſwered, that you offer the blind, the lame, and the maimed: vnto the holie miniſtery, and ſay it is no euill, and ſo diſpiſe the Lords name, bicauſe you ſay the Lords miniſtery is not to be regarded. For ſeeing you your ſelues knowe, and all VVales knoweth, that you haue admitted vnto this ſacred function, rogues, and vacabounds, gadding about the countrey, vnder the names of ſchollers, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts, and ſeruing men, that made the miniſterie their laſt refuge, ſeeing you permit ſuch to bee in the miniſterye, as are knowen adulterers, knowen drunkardes, theeues, roiſters, moſt abhominable ſwearers, euen the men of whome Iob ſpeaketh,<note n="c" place="margin">Iob. 30.1.8.</note> who are more vile then the earth, doe you not ſay that the Lords ſeruice is not to be regarded? if you any longer either tollerate others, or continue your ſelues to bee theeuiſhe non-reſidents, and ſo ſterue the ſoules of poore innocents, do you regard the Lords honour, and the ſaluation of his people?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181007:12"/>Is the law of truth ſound in your mouthes? Do ye conuert any from iniquitie? It ſhould be ſo indeed.<note n="a" place="margin">Mala. 1.7.</note> For your lips ſhould preſerue knowledge, and the ignorant ſhould ſeeke the law at your mouthes, for you ought to bee the meſſengers of Iehouah<note n="b" place="margin">Mala. 2.9.</note> of hoſts. But may this teſtimony bee giuen of you? I feare me no: Nay rather bicauſe all the world ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that iudgement vppon you, which the prophet denounced againſt the prelats of his daies, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that you are vile and contemptible in the ſight of the people, (for what is more contemptible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the beſt, and baſeſt of our people, then to be a Prieſt, yea a prieſtly Lord-Biſhop) I can iudge no otherwiſe of you, but that you haue not kepte the waies of Iehouah, gone out of the way, cauſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to fall by the law,<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 33.10. mala. 2.6.</note> and corrupted the couenant of Leuy. And will you ſtill continue in theſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, God forbidde. Be awakened nowe at the length, conſidering where vnto you are called. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo that calling no longer which you are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcharge, I ſpeake vnto you all, euen vnto you that will be accounted Lord-Biſhops, though it bee to the Lordes<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 22 25. 1. pet. 5.3. mar. 10.43.43. ier. 5.31.</note> diſhonour. Let the curſſe of damned ſoules cleaue no longer vnto you. For it perceth deeply. You are one day to giue a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for your mercileſſe dealing with pore ſoules. Let not the wicked Papiſts haue anye more cauſe to vpbraid the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our people, as they haue done in that pamphlet which they threwe abroad the laſt year, to ſeduce our ſimple people. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation wherof (if legendarie fables wherewyth that skroul is fraught, the tranſlation of ſome part of R.P. his reſolution, of Didachus Stella, Dionyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Carthuſ. deſerueth a confutation, I ſhall publiſh when the Lord ſhall giue oportunitie. If their bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181007:12"/>ſlaunders will not mooue you, let the wordes of Paule ſtirre you forward, whereby from heauen in moſt Patheticall and earneſt ſort he ſpeaketh vnto euerie one of you ſeuerally, in the perſon of Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie<note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1.2.</note>
               <note n="(41)" place="margin">41</note> I adiure or charge thee therefore ſayth he, before God, and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, preach the woord, be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, improue, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and doctrine. Obey this charge, or doubtles, moſt irkſom ſhalbe your da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. Is it not a ſhame that Ieremie may crye,<note n="b" place="margin">Iere. 27.1.</note> that our lande is defiled by ſuch as you are, yea &amp; in my houſe haue I found their wickednes, ſaith Iehouah? Are not we the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitaunts of Wales, as odious in the ſight of our God as the inhabitants of Gommorrah, ſeeing he<note n="c" place="margin">Iere. 8.14.</note> ſeeth filthines in you our prophets, and euerie of you from the greateſt to the loweſt, is giuen to couetouſneſſe, and dealeth falſelye.<note n="d" place="margin">Iere. 23.14.</note> And what with your loitring, idleneſſe, inſufficiencie, and euil life,<note n="e" place="margin">Iud. 11.</note> you ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, that none can returne from his wickednes. Wo be vnto you all, for you haue followed the waye of Caine, and are caſt away by the deceit of Baalams wages. Woe bee vnto you that account it pleaſure to liue delitiouſly for a ſeaſon, vppon the price of ſoules, you ſhal receue the wages of vnrighteouſnes,<note n="f" place="margin">2. Pet, 2.13.</note> we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnaſhing of teeth in the pit of hell.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.15.</note> What comfort is it for you to forſake the right way for a little worldly promotion, ſeeing the blacknes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting deſtruction is reſerued for you? What maye hir Maieſtie and the H. I. L. of hir counſell, thinke you to be, but the curſſed ſhepheards that ſcatter their flockes, ſeeing you haue not turned your people from their euill waies.<note n="h" place="margin">Ierem. 23.22.</note> Ieremy proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you to be ſuch. Therefore wo be to the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181007:13"/>of Wales, ſaith Iehouah, which feede them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſhould not the ſhepheards feed their flocks, you eat the far and cloath you with the wooll,<note n="a" place="margin">Ezech. 34.23</note> but you feede not the flocke. The ſentence pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Lord againſt you<note n="b" place="margin">Ezech. 34.10.</note> ſhalbe execured with out doubt in the time thereof, if you continue ſtill in your vngodlye courſe. Take this from mee alſo, that vnleſſe you forſake your idlenes, thoſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages and thoſe chaires of peſtilence wherein you ſit, I mean your Biſhops ſeas will ſpue you out. And the Lorde I hope will make them ſo abhominable, and reprochfull, that all men fearing God, will be afraid hereafter to enter into thoſe ſeas of Dauids, Aſaph, Bangor, and Landaff, by reaſon of the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of ſure deſtruction, that hee will imprint on as manie as ſhall ſupplie your places. And I truſt in the Lord Ieſus, to ſee his church floriſh in wales, when the memorie of Lord-Biſhops are buried in hell whence they came. Beare witneſſe hereof you adges to come. And giue you ouer your places, or doutleſſe, the plague and curſſe of God will eat you vppe, You are vſurpers, you tyrannize ouer the Lords people.</p>
            <p>I haue other things to do then to be a contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, one with whome the whole world ſhould be at debate, and I am guiltie vnto my ſelfe of ſins, which giue me iuſt cauſe to look vpon the ground: I haue alſo a life, whereof there is no cauſe I thanke God I ſhould bee weary, notwithſtanding this I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, to looſe the life of my body before man, and the life of my ſoule before the Lord, if I do not prooue, that both you our non-reſidents, and you our Lord Biſhops of VVales, in that you be non-reſidents and Lord-Biſhops, cannot be warranted by gods word: yea, or vtterly condemned by the ſame, and that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181007:13"/>all magiſtrates who tollerate ſuch as you are, to be vnder their gouernment, are guiltie of a fearefull ſinne before the Lord. And that the Pope of Rome hath as good warrant, yea the verie ſame warrant, for his papall dignitie (although I know three dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betweene you and him: firſt, hee is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Idolater, ſecondlie, claimeth authority ouer all paſtors: thirdly, is ſubiect to no ciuill magiſtrat) that you haue for the maintenance of your papall hierarchy ouer al the Paſtors in your dioces, which indeed is palpable Anarchie in Gods church. If I proue not theſe things, let me be burnt aliue, cal me to mine anſwere when you wil, &amp; thus I leaue you.</p>
            <p>As for you, our dumbe miniſters, I know you for the moſt part to be ſeelie men, poore ſoules, that made the miniſtery, a meanes to liue in the world. What ſhould I ſay vnto you, who maye ſay of your ſelues, as did the fooliſhe Prophetes. Though wee weare a ſurplice, &amp; black garments to deceiue,<note n="a" place="margin">Zach. 13.5.</note>
               <note n="(42)" place="margin">42</note> yet are we but plaine husbandmen, &amp;c. Surelie the people may aske counſell as well of their threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlds, or deſire their ſtaffes to teach them know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as come vnto you for anie inſtruction. You are no miniſters as I haue, and againe wil prooue, you do moſt villanouſly prophane the ſacraments, and call for the wrath and vengeance of God to be powred vpon you.<note n="(43)" place="margin">43</note> Giue ouer your places, or ſurely, I do not ſee how it is poſſible you ſhould be ſaued. Better were it to liue poorelye heere for a time, then to be damned for euer. It is reaſon your outward eſtate ſhould bee conſidered. The Lorde will prouide for you, your wiues, and chidren, if of conſcience you leaue the miniſtery, and the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is bound not to ſee you want. You liue nowe vppon ſtealth, ſacriledge, and the ſpoile of ſoules
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181007:14"/>The Lord open your eies my brethren, the people of VVales, to ſee theſe your plagues, and to auoid them. It is vnpoſſible you ſhould be ſaued as long as you content your ſelues with theſe men &amp; their miniſterie alone. And the Lord open your Honors eies to reforme theſe confuſions.</p>
            <p>What the eſtate of my countrie is, before the Lorde I haue hitherto ſhewed, nowe in the face of the world, how it ſtandeth let vs conſider. That the moſt congregations in VVales, haue wanted prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching theſe nine and twenty yeres, I take it graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Their caſe being thus, I tremble to cal to mind what cenſure the holie ghoſt giueth of all them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt whome the Goſpell of ſaluation hath not bin preached. Theſe two places of ſcripture (Epheſ. 1.13. &amp; 2.11.17.) conferred togither, ſhew that they are without Chriſt, aliants fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the common-welth of Iſrael, haue no hope, and are without God in the world (for theſe be the verie wordes of the apoſtle) who haue not heard of the word preached. VVere the Prophet Ionas then now liuing among vs, wold he not crie out? O you people of Wales, you are al reprobats and caſt-aways, O you people of Wales, you are aliaunts from the communion of the true Churche, O you people of Wales, you are not ſo much as encluded within the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of promiſe, you are without al hope of heauenly blis, O ye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Wales, whatſoeuer you pretend of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true God, you are in very deede ſtarke atheiſts &amp; without god, as many of you as ſince the time you came out of the den of idolatrie and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, were not made pertakers of the power of God to ſaluation, which is the goſpell. Of a truth, my brethren, there is no other true cenſure to bee giuen of you.<note n="(44)" place="margin">44</note> For it is impoſſible to make a true
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181007:14"/>face of a Church appear among that nation, which hath profeſſed falſe religion (as you haue done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der poperie) without the preaching of the woorde, which you haue not enioyed. In this place, I am ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I am ſorie from my heart, that the miſerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of my poore countrey affoordeth the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie ſuch a demonſtration, to proue, that we want the outwarde face of a church in the moſt aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies in Wales, as I know to be vnanſwerable. The marks of a true church,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28.18.19.</note> out of our ſauiour Chriſts owne wordes are gathered to be three, the woord preached, the right adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and the outwarde forme of gouernement. Now if an Idolatrous dog of Rome ſhould affirme, that the moſt congregations in Wales, ſince the time they were Romiſh ſinagogues, haue bin mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with neither of theſe three former markes, and therefore muſt bee written in the blacke bill of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie, to be churches of God, hee were able to prooue both the one and the other, and we with confuſion of face ſhould bee driuen with Hezekias ſeruants to anſwer this Rabſhaketh not a word. For<note n="b" place="margin">2. King. 18.36.</note> alas, what might be our anſwere?<note n="c" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.21.</note> Begotten again out of the wombe, of popery by the word preached, moſt of our aſſemblies haue not beene. As for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, our Prophets are not aſhamed publikelie to profeſſe, that they will not bee reformed by it. If we would flie vnto the teſtimonies that wee might haue from the Sacraments, the Lord himſelfe will denie it to be poſſible for them, to haue bene right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vſed among vs. Which I wil proue by many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that my countrey-men may be driuen to ſeek the remedie (if anye thing can driue them) of ſuch a pitifull condition, as wherein they nowe are, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without the woord, without the true vſe of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181007:15"/>Sacraments, without Chriſtes holy gouernement) by the knowlege of that righteous one, who is ſaid<note n="a" place="margin">Eſay. 53.11.</note> thereby to iuſtifie many. Let no man doe me the iniurie, to report that I denie anye members of Chriſt to be in Wales, I proteſt I haue no ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and would die vpon the perſwaſion, that the lorde hath his choſen in my deare countrie, and I truſt the number of them will be dailie increaſed. To come to the point, I affirme that the lords holy Sacraments, in the moſt churches within Wales, are ſubiect vnto moſt horrible profanation, as well on the behalfe of the reader, who adminiſtreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the people who communicate. So that a reading miniſter<note n="(45)" place="margin">45</note> cannot deliuer the Lords holie ſeales vnto the people without great ſacriledge, nor the people receue at the hands of ſuch, without dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſins. And that not onely becauſe the outward elements is adminiſtred without the woorde, euen vnto a people who neuer hadde Chriſt Ieſus laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto them in all their liues: but alſo in as much as they are deliuered by theſe perſons, vnto whom the Lord neuer warranted by his word the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of that function. Now that the Lord alowes none of our bare readers to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I haue before ſhewed by the manifold rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alleadged to prooue them no miniſters, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, do manifeſt by theſe following. Deſiring my godlie learned &amp; reuerend brethren, who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie &amp; as they ſhalbe found, to thinke of the concluſion. I deale not in this argument of anie ſingularitie, but becauſe I knowe, that vnleſſe theſe emptye caskes be ſuncke vnder water, Chriſtes kingdome is neuer likely to ſwimme.</p>
            <p>That my reaſons may be the better vnderſtood,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:181007:15"/>we are to marke: firſt, that all men being alike vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually capable of the miniſterie by nature, none are to vndergo this calling, ſaue onely they, whome the Lorde in his worde hath pronounced to be capable hereof. Againe, wee are to knowe, that wee ought to account none to be a miniſter, whome the Lorde accounteth not to bee ſuche: for, muſt Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, or mans pleaſure take place in that choice? So that although all the Churches vnder Heauen, ſhoulde make him a miniſter, whom the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth to be capable of that function, it is nothing. I aſſume then, that no bare reader is capable of the miniſterie before GOD. Confirmed,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2. 1. Cor. 4 7. Eph. 3.7. Hebr. 5.1.4. 1. Pet. 4.10. Ierem. 14.14. and 29 9.</note> becauſe the Lord hath not qualified him with gifts fitte for that function, and therefore he neither is miniſter, nor ought to be acknowledged of Gods people as a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. Out of this concluſion I reaſon, whoſoeuer receyue the ſacraments at their hands, whom they ought not to acknowledge miniſters, they ſinne. Dumb miniſters, (I doo not tie my ſelfe vnto exact formes in my ſyllogiſmes) ought not to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged miniſters, therefore it is a ſinne to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with them, which no man ſhoulde committe to ſaue his ſoule, much leſſe to receiue the ſeales of ſaluation. Yea, but we muſt acknowledge them miniſters for their outward callings ſake. This obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is nothing elſe but a deniall of the concluſion. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thus ouerthrow it: they of<note n="(2)" place="margin">2</note> whoſe miniſterie there is a nullitie before God, although they haue an outward calling, ought not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted miniſters, and therefore not to be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated with. For, may we allow of that wherof the Lord diſliketh? Where is our warrant? The Church can not make good a meaner thing than this, as for example: The Church maketh an inceſtuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:181007:16"/>the parties are married, I demaund whether the marriage be allowable, or they inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſtill? All men, I knowe will crie for a diuorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now there is as vngodly a match made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a reader and an holie congregation, muſt it ſtand becauſe the church alloweth of it? Or may the congregation vſe him in the ſacraments or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dueties eſſential vnto a miniſter? Out vpon it, no: for the contract was inceſtuous, and therefore not effectuall. The aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that of an inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent mans miniſterie there is a nullitie before God, though he haue an inwarde calling, becauſe it was neuer any thing as yet in his ſight.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, we are to call to minde, that in a miniſter there is required, firſt an outward calling contained in the ſufficiencie of gifts,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.1.</note> and the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to practiſe them: ſecondly, an outwarde which the church according vnto the ordinaunce of God is to giue onelie where the Lorde will haue it beſtowed, and not elſe-where. This outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling being once giuen, can be taken away by none but by the Lord, who gaue it. For the calling is not from man, but from the Lord by the hands of man, as by an inſtrument. Where alſo wee learne twoo things: firſt, that he is not a miniſter according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods ordinance, which wanteth either of theſe callings. Now<note n="(3)" place="margin">3</note> I aske the queſtion, whether the ſacrament may be receiued at his hands, who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, but that which man can giue vnto him, to wit, his outward calling? In no wiſe. And may we then receiue at his hands, who is deſtitute of the inward graces, which neither man nor aungell can giue? Vnreaſonable: ſecondlie, wee learne that of thoſe menne who haue an outwarde callinge, there bee two ſortes, whoſe miniſterye is annihilated before
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181007:16"/>God, though all the world ſhould go about to make it good. The firſt is of thoſe, who hauing an inward and an outward calling, are notwithſtanding repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from this function. And they are either ſuch, as from whom the Lord in his ſecret prouidence hath taken away their fitneſſe to teach,<note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.2 1 Tim. 4.2. Ezech. 4.4.10 12</note> or thoſe, who by ſome notorious ſinne, haue fruſtrated their calling, whome the church vppon their repentaunce ought to receiue as brethren, but neuer as miniſters. The ſecond ſort of thoſe whoſe outward caling, is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than abhominable incenſe in the lords noſtrels, is of them, who neuer had anie abilitie for the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, as infants, dumbe men by nature, dumbe men in regarde of their inſufficiencie to vtter the Lordes meſſage. The outward calling of theſe, yea, by all the presbyteries in the worlde, is but a ſeale preſt vppon water, which will receiue no impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Howe much leſſe authenticall is a corrupt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be accounted? The reaſon for the defence of the outward calling of idoll-miniſters, which is drawen from the example of the prophets,<note n="b" place="margin">Iſay. 66.10, 11. Zach. 11.17.</note> who did not diſſuade the people of their time from the dumb dogs, againſt whom they crie out, is ſo ſeelie, that it deſerueth no anſwere. For wee reade,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Chro. 29.6, 7 Iſay. 1.1.</note> that the people liuing in Iſaiah his owne time, either vnder Hhuzzia, Iotham, or Achas, who was the greateſt aduerſarie that euer the dumb Leuites had, neither burnt incenſe nor offered burnt offerings vnto the God of Iſraell, miſſe not to reade the place<note n="d" place="margin">2. Chro. 29.6, 7</note> Where didde Iſaiah reprooue this? No where that wee can reade. Now what an horrible thing were it for a prince to expell the publike ſeruice of God out of his dominion, or neglect the ſame, and defend this practiſe as approoued by the word, becauſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did not reprooue the like ſinne committed in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181007:17"/>their dayes, and yet this reaſon woulde haue ſome more ſtuffe in it, than the other for the dumbe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie? I coulde be well as large in ſhewing the inſufficiencie of the reaſon, as I haue beene already in the whole treatiſe. But I make ſome conſcience of being tedious, and therefore I content my ſelfe with this I haue ſpoken, being ready many wayes to make the weakeneſſe of it appeare when it ſhall be requiſite, I go forward.</p>
            <p>They<note n="(4)" place="margin">4</note> of whom the Lorde ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">Ierem. 23.21.</note> I haue not ſent theſe, although they runne, I haue giuen them no commiſſion to deliuer a Sacrament, although they are permitted to profane the outward ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are no miniſters, and it is a ſinne to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with them. They are no miniſters, becauſe the Lord ſent them not. Do not miſtake me,<note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 7.22.</note> for a wicked hypocrite is ſometimes ſent of the Lord. It is a ſinne to receiue at their hands, becauſe we can not ground our aſſurance vpon the Lords promiſe, that we may haue a Sacrament by their miniſterie. For the Lorde hauing giuen them no allowance to deliuer the ſame, haue we anie promiſe to receiue it of them? So that the Lorde may ſay vnto vs; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and you will, of vnpreaching miniſters, for aught you knowe, it is no ſacrament. Another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note n="(5)" place="margin">5</note> whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne, but to communicate with vnſufficient men, is not of faith, bicauſe we haue no promiſe that they can deliuer vs the Sacraments, and therfore to communicate with ſuch, is a ſinne. Againe we<note n="(6)" place="margin">6</note> haue no warrant to receiue an<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> extraordinary ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but that which is adminiſtred, by ignorant miniſters, is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie ſacrament, if it be any. (Becauſe, according vnto the ordinance of God, a preacher is onelie to deliuer the ſame) therefore we haue no warrant to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:181007:17"/>receiue it. And what dare wee vndertake with out warrant from the Lordes mouth? Belike then, will ſome man ſay, that is no Sacrament which hath bin adminiſtred by theſe who were not preachers, and ſo the moſt nowe liuing in this age, are either not baptized, or muſt be rebaptized. The diſgrace that is brought vpon the cauſe, as though it went aboute to enforce rebaptiſation, is eaſilie wiped away. For the action performed is not denied to be a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: though it were,<note place="margin">As I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that whiche hath bene done to bee a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence. ſo if any can proue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it to be non, I wil not withſtand him.</note> yet I would wiſh none to be rebapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, for many cauſes. Firſt, we are already receiued into the boſome of the church, and acknowledged to haue the ſeale of the couenant, in as much as wee were once offered and receiued into the number of the godly, by the outward element, though corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. To what ende then ſhoulde baptiſme ſerue vs againe? Secondly, the abſolute neceſſitie of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to ſaluation by this meanes might ſeeme to be maintained. Thirdly, leaſt we ſhoulde ſeeme to agree with the hereticall Katabaptiſts.<note place="margin">If theſe reaſons can be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I ſee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereſie nor error in being rebaptized.</note> Fourthlye, other Churches haue not publikelie decided the cauſe. Fiftly, that the practiſe ſhoulde not inforce them to be rebaptized, which haue beene alreadie baptized, by ſuch as had commiſſion from the Lord to deale in thoſe myſteries. Laſtly, they who (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now in the age of diſcretion) haue beene bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by idoll-miniſters, are either called or not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſaluation: if called, why ſhould they be rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, ſeeing alreadie they haue beene made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the outward element, and accounted in the number of chriſtians? If not called, neither ſhould they be baptized, vntill they declared by their works that they were Gods children. Concerning the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie then, whether the element adminiſtred by an ignorant man, be a ſacrament, being once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181007:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:181007:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:181007:19"/>deliuered, I would wiſhe all men in modeſtie to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from ſo vngodlie a iar, becauſe it tendeth not to edificaion, and it is not the point, it is not the queſtion. A priuate communion miniſtred to one alone may be a ſacrament. What then? are men to receiue at home beeing ſicke? No, for it is a ſinfull breach of Gods inſtitution. In like ſort, Baptiſme, or the Lords ſupper adminiſtred by a dumbe miniſter, may be a ſacrament,<note place="margin">I affirme rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be no miniſters, &amp; for any thing that is raueled in the word, that they can deliuer no ſacrament, and yet that which hath bene done by them may be be a ſacrament, and what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie is there id theſe aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> is it therfore lawfull to receiue it. In no wiſe, becauſe it is a ſinne, and that is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to terrifie anie from that action. It hath beene before conuinced for a ſinne, and again is thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be no leſſe. It (7) is a ſinne, either to receiue the Sacraments at the handes of thoſe, who are not miniſters, or to teſtifie them to bee miniſters, vnto whom the Lord hath denied that function. But they that communicate with dumbe miniſters, committe either of theſe ſinnes. If they ſaye they doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue at their handes who are not Miniſters, then they teſtifie them to be miniſters, and ſo are fonnde to gaine-ſay the Lord. For they ſay readers are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, the Lord ſaith no. Whether ſhall we beleue? That,<note place="margin">7</note> the Lord ſayth no, and prooueth it no, I thus prooue. Hee ſayth that there is no miniſter,<note n="a" place="margin">Mark. 28. mar. 16.16.1. cor. 3.7.1. pet. 4.10.</note> but a preaching miniſter by his inſtitution. If it be thoght other-wiſe, then it muſt be prooued that the Lorde in his word hath ordayned (els the confuſion that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery priuat ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may adminiſter the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts muſt enſue) two ſortes of miniſters to deliuer the ſeales of ſaluation, the one preachers, the other not able to preach. Shew an vnpreaching miniſter out of the woord, and I will yeelde. Out of this reaſon, manie arguments might bee drawen. As firſt, that readers (8) are not miniſters of<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 21. rom. 10.14.1. pet. 2.5. &amp; 2.22.</note> ſaluation,<note place="margin">8</note> and therefore ought not to deale with the ſeales thereof. Secondly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:181007:19"/>they can not (9) increaſe our vnion with Chriſte.<note place="margin">9</note> Thirdly, are of them ſelues miniſters,<note place="margin">10</note> (10) of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation onely, becauſe that keeping men from the foode of life, they ſtarue them, and ſo worke their damnation with manye other which I omitte, ſaue theſe following. We neither (11) ought to receiue at their handes,<note place="margin">11</note> neither ought they to deliuer the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments vnto vs, who haue not power by vertue of their publike miniſterie to engraffe an infidell into Chriſt. Bare readers haue not this power. For by vertue of the publike miniſterie, this is the proper worke of a Preacher, therefore they neither ought<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> to deliuer the ſacramentes vnto vs, neither ought we to communicate with them. Further,<note place="margin">12</note> (12) they that come to a publike miniſter rather then to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man for the ſeales of ſaluation, either profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſider not what they doe, or profeſſe that they would haue the aſſurance of no other ſaluation and no other Chriſt, then of that Chriſt, and that ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereof hee that adminiſtreth hath warraunt from the Lord to aſſure them off. This warrant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe meere readers haue not, it followeth that in communicating with them, men either profanelie conſider not what they doe, or make choyce of a falſe Chriſt, and a deceiuable ſaluation. Becauſe they will haue no other Chriſt, and no other ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then that Chriſt, and that ſaluation, the ſeales whereof ignorant miniſters haue commiſſion from the Lord to deliuer, which indeede is no Chriſt and no ſaluation.<note place="margin">13</note> Laſtly (13) where as by Baptiſme I am iovned vnto the ſocietie of Chriſtians, I declare thereby that if there bee no ſaluation to be hadde among them, I will not be ſaued, but am content to be a caſt-away for euer. Nowe alacke if he that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtreth, hath no warrant to receiue me into this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:181007:20"/>company, what comfort can I haue by that action. Though the Lord in mercie make it an authenticall Sacrament, I could be aſſured of no ſuch thing. My good brethren, conſider therefore what you doe, in permitting your children to bee baptized by your dumbe miniſters, conſider what you do in receiuing the Lords Supper, at their handes. Would you haue your children ingraffed into (your ſelues aſſured of) no other Chriſt, then theſe your ſimple readers can laie open? If you would, aduenture no more to deal with them. Of a truth my brethren, your ſinne hath bene alreadie vnmeaſurably great. Repent, repent, and that betimes. Fall downe before the Lorde, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to forgiue you. And ſinne no more in this execrable profanation of Gods holie miſteries; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to haue true Paſtors placed ouer you, and reſt not vntill you haue broght this to paſſe. In the mean time carrie your children a 1000. miles to a true miniſter of God to bee baptized, rather then offer them vnto your hierlings. Yea if you cannot when you haue done al you can, get baptiſme without the breach of Gods inſtitution (as God be thanked, you may vnder her Maieſtie) leaue them vnbaptized. An intollerable ſpeach (will ſome ſay) in this age; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and vngodly age, wherein to affirme, that it is not lawfull to breake the lawe of the eternall, is thought intollerable.<note place="margin">1</note> Is it not prooued a(1) ſinne to communicate with our wicked blind Paſtours, and hath this age,<note place="margin">2</note> any diſpenſation to ſinne. Hhuzzah(2) ſhould not haue offended, for not vpholding the ark<note n="a" place="margin">Sam. 67.8. nb. 4.15.</note> although the ſame hadde beene broken in ſhiuers, where as the verie touching of it, contrarie to the commaundement of God, euen to ſtaye it from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, coſt him his life. And ſhall wee eſcape, if wee breake Gods holy inſtitution in the Baptiſme of our,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:181007:20"/>children, aſſuredlie no. To (3) omitte a ſinne is no ſinne, and therefore to omitte baptiſme, if it cannot be gotten without ſinne, is lawfull. It (4) is not the omiſſion, but the careleſſe and negligent ſeeking offend not this way in anie caſe, or the wilfull or vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contempt of Baptiſme, that diſpleaſeth the Lord. The Iſraelites (5) ſhould haue ſinned in offering<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 12.5.4.1. king 8.29.</note> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifice out of Ieruſalem, and therefore all the time of their captiuitie in Babylon, they would be with-but that comfort of their faith rather then offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. So ought we rather to want the ſacraments, then ſinne by inioyning of them.</p>
            <p>Your Honour is cited in this place my Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods tribunall ſeat, and charged in the name of the etereall and almightie God, as you ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere at the dreadfull daie of iudgement, that you ſuffer not his holie miſteries any more to bee profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, where your authority may withſtand the ſame. A word of your mouth might reſtraine the flood of this pollution. The Lorde giue you a feeling and an vnderſtanding heart. Remember the godlie rulers, and noble men that haue beene before you. Moſes, Iehoſhuah, Dauid, Salomon, Iehoſaphat, Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, Ioſhiah, Hebedmelech, Nehemiah with the reſt, who nowe reſt with the Lord.<note n="b" place="margin">Exo. 32.31.32.</note> Fall downe before your God with Moſes, and ſay, O this people haue ſinned a great ſinne, in liuing all this while without the word preached, in ſuffering their children to be baptized of ignorant miniſters, therefore now wilt thou pardon their ſinne.<note n="c" place="margin">Nomb. 14.17.</note> And now I beſeech thee, let the power of my Lord appeare, as thou haſt ſaid, Iehouah is ſlow to anger, &amp;c. Be mercifull I beſeech thee vnto this people, &amp;c. and the Lorde I truſt will anſwere your honour as he did Moſes, I haue pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them according vnto thy requeſt. Bleſſed, yea,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:181007:21"/>ten thouſand times bleſſed, were your people, if you made ſuch a prayer for them, and receiued ſuch an anſwere.</p>
            <p>Well, the condicion of my deere countrie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus fearefull before the Lorde, and damnable in the ſight of the world, what is nowe to bee doone that it may bee bettered? Verily this, procure you the woorde preached, for your ſelues and obay the ſame, or els woe woorth you, woe woorth you, I ſay Magiſtrates, Gentlemen, Miniſters, and people, for otherwiſe you reiect Ieſus Chriſt, and wil not haue him to raigne ouer you. I haue ſet downe the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ordinarie waye to ſaluation, the Lorde, for the maintenaunce of the eſtate of any of you, will not finde another though he may. Therefore enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this, or be damned. For ſhall the higheſt make newe decrees, becauſe the ſonne of the clay, duſt, and aſhes, baſe and contemptible man, wyll not tread the olde and auncient pathes? No.</p>
            <p>You muſt not onelie haue the worde, but obey, it in euerie point and ſhewe by your good workes, that indeed it hath bene ſowen among you. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if you meane to bee like the common profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of theſe daies, who couenaunt before hande with the Lord, that their pride and eſtate muſt bee maintained whatſoeuer he requireth who are more buſie to woonder at other mens infirmities, then to beate downe their owne ſinnes, who will not dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh one ior of their horrible couetouſneſſe, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of their tenaunts, looſe one gry of their whooriſh pompe, and more than curtiſanlike braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, though the truth ſhould in the meane time bee gored through with ſlaunders, preſume not once to open your mouthes for the woord preached, vnleſſe you woulde aggrauate your owne damnation. For
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:181007:21"/>aſſure your ſelues heoreof, that the popiſh Idolaters the atheiſts and ſwiniſh epicures of theſe daies, who haue bidden battell vnto all religion and honeſtie, ſhal feel of the fierce wrath of god in the life to com, but as for the mocke-Gods, I meane the common Proteſtants of this age, who thinke they doe a meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious worke, becauſe they intertaine the word in their families, yea do not expell the ſame, out of the places where they haue ought to doe, woe bee vnto them<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 11.21.</note> for they ſhall be like Corazin, they ſhall bee like Bethſaida, they ſhall bee like Capernaum.</p>
            <p>The worde preached you ſee you muſt haue, liue according vnto it you muſt, ſerue the Lorde as hee willeth, in euerie point you muſt, or ſoake for euer in your owne confuſion. Difficulties in this caſe muſt not bee alleadged, for if you ſeeke the Lorde with a ſure purpoſe to ſerue him, hee hath made a promiſe to be found of you.<note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 2.16.</note> Away then with thoſe ſpeaches, how can we be prouided of preaching; our liuinges are impropriated, poſſeſſed by ſwine, as nonreſidents and hierlings. Come by it as you can, you ſhall goe to hell, vnleſſe you haue it. A goodlie matter. Is there no way to remooue theſe beaſts, by ſupplication to hir Maieſtie, &amp;c. and to place better in their ſteade; Indeede you will ſeeke none: Be it you can not remooue them. Can you beſtowe noe more to be inſtructed in the waye of life, then that which law alreadie hath allienated from your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions. You neuer made account of your tythes, as of your owne. For ſhame beſtow ſome thing that is yours, to haue ſaluation made knowen vnto you. Contemne not the grace of God offered vnto you in theſe daies of your peace. For if you refuſe to com vnto the Lord when he calleth, behold your anſwer when you call for mercy at his handse. There is a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:181007:22"/>time<note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 1.24.30.</note> of repentaunce indeede, but that is limited according vnto the Lords will and not mans.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I take the paines to ſhewe howe miniſters, and their liuings may bee prouided for in Wales? Seeing I ſee none readie as yet to entertain the worde, and that which hath bene done hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this point, is not practized. When anye are willing to entertaine counſell for this matter, I dout not, but it will be an eaſie conſultation. Not to doe in ſome place what may bee doone, becauſe euerie place cannot bee furniſhed with learned miniſters, and their liuinges is but to deride the Lorde to his face, and delude his people of their ſaluation.</p>
            <p>The inhabitants of the citie Thaſus, being beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Athenians, made a lawe that whoſoeuer would motion a peaco to bee concluded with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, ſhdulde die the death. Their citie began to bee diſtreſſed, the people to periſhe, both with the ſwoorde and famine. Hegetorides a citizen, pitying the eſtate of his countrey, tooke an halter about his necke, came into the iudgement place: Spake. My maiſters, deale with me as you will, but in any caſe, make peace with the Athenians, that my countrey may be ſaued by my death. My caſe is like this mans. I know not my daunger in wtiting theſe things. I ſee you my dere &amp; natiue countrimen periſh. It pitieth me; I come with the rope about my necke to ſaue you, howſoeuer it goeth with me; I labour that you may haue the Goſpel preached among you, though it coſt mee my life: I thinke it well boſtowed. And ſeing I ſeeke nothing hereby but the glorie of God and your ſaluation, what deuils will be ſo ſhameles as to moleſt me for this worke, and hinder the word preached. If any ſuch ſhall bee found, I wiſhe them to conſider, before the deale with me what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:181007:22"/>ſetteth downe,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.15.</note> concerning the perſecutours of thoſe that ſeeke for preaching, and the hinderers thereof, namely that they pleaſe not God, and are euen contrarie vnto all men, and this their doing is a ſealed writing, that the vengeaunce of GOD will come vpon them to the full; Anſwere it howe they may. Be it as it will bee, my comfort is the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my conſcience, that in ſimplicitie and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, not onely, as in the ſight of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (vnto whoſe view and cenſure, this poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is offered) and his aungels, but as in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Ieſus Chriſt, I haue behaued my ſelf in this cauſe, hauing before mine eies that I am one day to yeeld an account vnto his maieſty, both of my good meaning, and alſo of all circumſtaunces, ouer-ſight, vaine and idle words, in the action. But alaſſe, what can proceed from me, that taſteth not of old Adam, and the bodie of ſinne which I carie about with me: wherſoeuer I haue offended, either in matter or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, let it be ſhewed, and I will with mine own hands deſtroy that which I haue built amiſſe, be ſorye for mine ouerſight, the moſt aeger cenſurer of my ſelfe, and thank them from my heart, who ſhall admoniſh mee of my fault. Yea, but the tractate concerning the Idoll miniſterie, tendeth to ſtirre vp my countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, hir Maieſties ſubiects, whereto? To feele in what a miſerable caſe they are before God, and the worlde, being without the word, without the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the ſacraments, and without Chriſtes holie diſcipline, and in regarde thereof, dutifully to entreat hir Maieſty, and their honors, that it may be redreſſed? Truth; And woulde to God they felt it. To miſlike of the eccleſiaſticall gouernement nowe eſtabliſhed among vs? truth, for it is forrain and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychriſtian for the moſt part. To miſlike of the ciuil
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:181007:23"/>gouernment; That is a ſlaunder, and I dare write in in my forhead for a ſlander. But why ſhould I deale in this cauſe more then others? The worthies of the Lord before me in preaching and writing for a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned miniſterie, ye haue dealt herein. If they hadde not, this is my reaſon. Though all hir Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, yea hir faithfulleſt counſellers ſhould conſpire againſt her highnes, I my ſelfe againſt them al wold defend hir, and her cauſe to the loſſe of my life ten thouſand times. And ſhall not I do the like ſeruice vnto the Lord?</p>
            <p>To ende, commending you all both honourable, worſhipfull, miniſters, and people, vnto the Lord and the worde of his grace, I take my leaue of you in that exhortation which wee read in Iob.<note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 23.21.22.25.</note> Acquaint your ſelues I pray you with the almightie, and make peace with him, thereby it ſhall go well with you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue I pray you, the law of his mouth, and lay vppe his wordes in your hearts. If you returne vnto him, you ſhalbe built vppe, if you put iniquitie farre from your tabernacle, the almightie ſhalbe your defence, you ſhall make your praier vnto him, and hee ſhall heare you. Chriſt Ieſus giue them an heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto thee, and be thou founde of them for thy mercies ſake. Amen, Amen, Amen. yea, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poore countrey-man, who in all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full good will, hath wholy dedicated him ſelfe to doe you good in the Lorde. IOHN PENRI.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:181007:23"/>
            <p>THus I haue ſet downe the exhortation, word for word, as it was in the former impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without the altering or deminiſhing of any one thing, (three marginall notes added) ſauing the faults eſcaped in the printing. And hauing heere and there diffuſed my reaſons againſt the dumb miniſters, which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue are not ſo eaſilie to bee gathered out of the ſame, becauſe the moſt part of them were brought in for other purpoſes; I thought good in this place, to ſet them downe ſyllogiſtically, to the end it maye appear vnto the church of God, vpon what grounds I denie them to be miniſters. But here firſt the ſtate of the queſtion is to be made knowen,<note place="margin">The ſlate of the queſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be anie miniſter at all, good or bad vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome the Lord neuer ſaid go and preach. Mat. 28.18.19. I denye ſuch a one to be any.</note> which is not whether our readers be ſuch, as haue the names, &amp; ſupplie the places of miniſters, (for he that will not graunt this, denieth heat to be in the fire) but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, by the vnlawfull conſent of our corrupt prelats, ſtealing the names, &amp; intruding themſelues vppon the places of miniſters, that is, hauing a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt outward calling, be miniſters indeede. So that for the better vnderſtanding of this controuerſie, I graunt, that in our Churche in thoſe daies of hir ruines, there bee two ſortes of miniſters. Firſt, a miniſter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> onely in name, which is not a miniſter indeed. Secondly, a miniſter both in name and deede: which alſo is double. Firſt, a miniſter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, hauing not only vpon him the name of a miniſter, but alſo in him theſe thinges which are agreeable vnto the name, and giue the eſſence and being therevnto. Secondly, a miniſter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which both carrieth the name, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the eſſence thereof, and laboureth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form indeed whatſoeuer belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto his calling, onely this miniſter is the good miniſter. As for the miniſters <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> if they bee not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:181007:24"/>they are all of them euill miniſters. Of the whiche crue, are all thoſe attainted with the faults ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.4.7.</note> in the worde; whome although by the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church, they ſhould bee compelled to leaue, either theyr faultes, or their miniſterie: yet I dare not deny to be miniſters, as long as the church tollerateth them, vnleſſe their offences bee ſuch, as preſently there enſueth<note n="b" place="margin">2. King. 23.9. Ezeb. 44.10.</note> a nullitie of their miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie before the Lord. Thoſe who are onely miniſters in name (of which ſorte by the reaſons following, I prooue all our readers to bee) are not miniſters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, and therefore can by no meanes be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted miniſters. Eſpeciallie, ſeeing as good and as able miniſters altogether as they are, might in ciuill pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie bee eſtabliſhed among the ſauadge Caniballs, who feed vpon mens fleſh, though they ſhould ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer any to come amongeſt them, that might teache them true religion, nor reſorte them ſelues where the ſame were profeſſed. For our Liturgie booke of Articles, manner of ordaining of Biſhops and Prieſts, articles agreed vpon by the cleargie, in the conuocation houſe, might bee tranſlated vnto their toong; &amp; they by a Lord-Archbiſhop or Biſhop, Caniball, might bee mad Deacons or foule Prieſts, to were a ſurplice, a cloake with ſleeues, a truncke gowne, a cap and tipper, and I thinke bell and babell (ornaments fit inogh for ſuch deformed coxcombs) to read a Goſpell, church women, bid faſting dayes, and holy-daies, profane the Sacramentes, praye at the buriall of the dead, pronounce a curſſe againſt ſinners vppon Aſh-wendſday, and at no time els, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a new Sacrament of the croſſe, in the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of baptiſme, viſit the ſicke with a wafer cake, and a wine-bottell, read Homilies, pray for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of theeues, pyrates, murtherers, yea, a Pope
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:181007:24"/>Cardinall, Arch-biſhop, Lord-biſhop, or any other enemie of God, &amp; his Church, if he trauaile by land or by water, and brieflie to performe whatſoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie reader within wales, by his outwarde calling is bound to do. Now any reaſonable man would denie theſe to be miniſters: howbeit they emoyed the names and roomes agreeable vnto that function. And I pray you, what difference ſhould there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe and our readers, in regard of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie? In their perſons I graunt ſome might bee ſhewed, but that can be nothing to make their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie diſagree. And this out of all controuerſie is moſt true, that no miniſterie can be where true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not, no miniſterie can be out of the church, as we ſee the miniſterie of our readers may. For the Apoſtle inſeperablie ioyneth the gathering' toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaints with the<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.22.</note> worke of the miniſterie.</p>
            <p>Where alſo the importunacie of the diſtinction that they are euill, that they are maimed miniſters, &amp; therfore miniſters is eſier anſwered then propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by granting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be euill &amp; may med miniſters indeed, but ſo euil and ſo maimed, as they are flatly none, &amp; ſo making 2. kinds of euill miniſters, the one ſo euil &amp; ſo maimed as they are none at al, the other in deede euill and maymed, but ſo as they want not the life, whereby a miniſter is a miniſter. A Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion entering into a campe of diſcomfited and wounded men, ſhoulde finde them all (it maye bee) wounded and maimed in moſt miſerable ſorte; but ſome ſo maimed, as they were not men, but deade corpſes. The ſame is to be ſaid of our foiled and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med miniſterie in this Lande, wherein all, from the higheſt to the loweſt (ſome few excepted which kepe vs from beeing like Sodome and Gomoraah (ſhalbe found mangled by Sathan (ſorrowfull and deſperate
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:181007:25"/>ſight:) in their verie eſſential parts, but ſome ſo mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that they are as dead as the doore naile. Now that all our readers want the very life, eſſence, and beeing whereby a miniſter is a miniſter, that is, are not miniſters in deed. I proue by theſe two reaſons, and haue prooued in the booke by the reaſons that ſhall enſue. Whoſoeuer wanteth that life, which is either preſcribed or included in the word, to be the life of a miniſter good or bad, hee hath not ſo much as the life of a badde miniſter, much leſſe of a good. But our readers want both that life, which is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed or included in the worde to be the life of a good miniſter, and that which is the life of a bad miniſter. Therefore our readers haue not ſo much as the life of a bad miniſter, much leſſe of a good; The propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is moſt manifeſt. For whence learne we, what giueth life and beeing vnto a miniſter, but out of the woorde? The prooſe of the aſſumption is thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. Firſt, there is no eſſence of that miniſter, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as good or as a bad miniſter, ſet downe to the worde, whereof there is at all no mencion made in worde. The truth hereof Appius Caecus might ſee. Doth the worde ſhewe what life and beeing hee can haue, whome it denieth to be at all? But our readers are not mentioned in the word as publik miniſters; Becauſe the word neuer dremt of that miniſter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome it is not ſayd: go<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 28.19</note> and teach. Therefore, there is no eſſence or life of our readers mentioned, off in the worde, either as good, or as bad miniſters. Secondly, there is no eſſence or life of that miniſter, either as a good or as a badde miniſter, ſet downe in the word, which is but the ordinance of the church, by the ordinance of the church, I mean euery mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery &amp; miniſter, which is not read of in the word, howſoeuer the outward calling be ioyned vnto it. I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:181007:25"/>know that the very outward calling of a miniſter, is not the ordinance of the church, but the inuiolable preſcript ordinance of God, in the deliuery wherof, the church is but an inſtrument, &amp; I can proue our readers to be neither the ordinance of God, nor of the church in that ſence, whereby the ordinance of the church is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the outward calling acording to the word; To the aſſumption. But our readers to make the moſt of them, are no more then the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the church. Therfore there is no eſſence or life of our readers ſet downe in the worde, either as good or bad miniſters. The aſſumption euerye man will graunt; the propoſition is moſt firme; Becauſe that euerie miniſter<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.4.11.28. &amp; 4.7. &amp; 9.16.17. 2 Cor: 4.6. Math: 21.25. &amp; 11.11. Rom. 12.6. Ephe: 4.11. Colloſir. 25.</note> good or<note n="b" place="margin">Phil: 1.15.16. 1. Cor: 3.3.15. Mat: 7.22. 1. Cor. 9.27.</note> bad, is the ordinance of God, in ſuch ſort, as to whome-ſoeuer the Lorde hath not committed<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.4. Iohns miniſterie was from God, therfore much more euery mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtery more euery mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in the king done vnder the goſpell. Math. 21.26. &amp; 11.11</note> the diſpenſation of his will, well he may haue the outward calling of a miniſter, he is in deede no more then the ordinaunce of the Church, and ſo wanteth the verie life of a miniſter. For it is not the approbation of the Church by the outward calling, that can giue life vnto that miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie which is not heard off in the worde. Becauſe the outwarde calling giueth not the life or beeing vnto a miniſter, but the birth. So that to make a miniſter, therebe two things required. Firſt, a being or life, which the Lord onely can giue. Secondlye, a birth, which the Church as an inſtrument of the ordinance of God, is to beſtow vpon him by his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling. Theſe two things are ſo eſſentially to be required in a miniſter, that whoſoeuer wanteth either of them, he cannot poſſibly be a miniſter. For where is that man that conſiſteth onelye of a ſoule, or onelye of a bodye? where is that man that neuer had life? Or what was is his name that neuer was borne? whervpon it enſueth, that neither he which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:181007:26"/>wanteth either of theſe two partes, muſte not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to intermeddle with thoſe actions, which are by the ordinance of God, neceſſarilie tied (as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes are) vnto him that hath both the life and the birth of a miniſter, nor I aduenture to goe vnto him for thoſe things, which he hath no commiſſion to deliuer. Be a man therefore neuer ſo godly, neuer ſo learned, endued with neuer ſo liuelye faculties of the miniſterie, yet he is no miniſter in deed, vnleſſe he haue the ordinaunce of his God vpon him by his outward calling. The preaching of the word being a gift, and not depending vpon the very ordination is not ſo tied to the perſon of a miniſter: but that he which hath not the outwarde calling, may offer the trial of his gifts vnto the church in the publik place, his ſpirite hauing before bene ſubiect vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> that is, ſuch as haue iudgement to diſcerne of his gifts. On the other ſide, beit that a man haue the outward calling of the church: yet in deede he is no miniſter, vnleſſe the Lord hath giuen him the life of a miniſter, by committing the woorde of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation vnto his hands. By this I haue ſet down two maine queſtions which trouble many that fear God in theſe daies are decided. Firſt, becauſe the outward calling is eſſentially required in a miniſter, it is therefore thought of ſome to be that, which gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the life vnto a miniſter. As though a childe hath not life in the wombe before it be born, or that his birth be any thing to giue him life: I graunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that a woman cannot glorie of the fruit of her body, vntill it come to the byrth, for the bignes of the woombe may proceede of ſome Tympany. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlye, in aſmuch as the manner of the eſſentiall birth of a miniſter, is preſcribed in the worde, which preſcript cannot without ſinne be altered by any, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:181007:26"/>in taking vpon them the miniſtery, or in impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame vpon others, ſome are ſeelilie carried away to thinke them, to be no miniſters which haue not their birth in euerye point according vnto this preſcription. The reaſon is no better, then if I ſhould denie him to be a true and a liuing childe, whome I cannot denie to haue the life &amp; the birth of a child, becauſe hee iſſued out at his birth by the waye hee ſhould not:<note place="margin">Tranq. in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. Caeſ.</note> if C. Iulins had beene taken out at hys mothers ſide, ſhoulde it therefore bee needleſſe to warne him to take heede of the Ides of March? ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon againſt theſe vntimely births, I thus frame; Whatſoeuer miniſterie and miniſter, was then vnknowen in the Church, when all thoſe callings flowriſhed therein, which were in any age, or time appointed by the Lord to be in the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; that miniſterie and miniſter hath not ſo much as the eſſence of a miniſterye or miniſter, good or bad; Euerie one knoweth this, who knoweth Paule to haue ſette downe, that the Lord<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.12.</note> ordained not a tranſitorie miniſterie, but ſuche as was to continue vntill his ſecond comming. And more then extream follie were it to thinke him, to ſet downe a being for that miniſter whom he neuer ment to ordain. But our readers &amp; their miniſtery were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnknown in the Church, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theſe callings flowriſhed therin, which the Lord in any age or time ordained for the miniſterie, I meane in the<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 12.3.7. 1. cor 12 28. epheſ. 4.12.13.</note> Apoſtles time. Therfore our readers and their miniſterie, haue not ſo much as the eſſence of a miniſterie or miniſters good or bad. Our of theſe two reaſons ariſe two proper dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, between the magiſtracy &amp; the miniſterie. Firſt, there may be a lawfull magiſtracie and magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate according to the woord, whoſe name and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:181007:27"/>was neuer heard of before in the worlde, much leſſe read in the word, ſo can there not be a miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or miniſter.<note place="margin">Tit. Liui. lib. 3. Cicero in 2. Cat</note> L. Quintius Cincinatus is made Dictator. L. Tarquinius maiſter of the horſe. L. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimius, the counſel muſt ſee that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth be not endaungered by any faction, the ſame place both before &amp; after ſuſtained many among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. In our time the care of the publike peace in all the Germaine empire, was committed to Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus a Schiuendi.<note place="margin">Iohn. Funccinus</note> All theſe were new kindes of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracies at their firſt inſtitution, yet lawfull. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond difference is, that the life and office of a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is preſcibed in the word, contained in his gifts, and ſeuered from his, outwarde calling. But the life of the magiſtracie, is neither preſcribed in the worde, (for ſo there coulde bee no magiſtrates out of the Church, nor any in the Church, but ſuch as are preſcribed in the worde, which were verie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious to thinke) or contained in the gifts of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grſtracie, not yet ſeperated from his outwarde cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For the verie outward calling is it, that giueth life vnto the magiſtracie, though the perſon ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, want gifts to diſcharge the ſame. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon heereof is euident, becauſe the magiſtracie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an humane conſtitution<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> as the holy ghoſt ſaith, is appropriated vnto his poſſeſſion vpon whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man beſtoweth the ſame, if hee bee capable to poſſeſſe (though vnfit to execute) what is allotted vnto him. So cannot the miniſterie bee, vnleſſe hee vpon whome the Church impoſeth it, be made fitte by the Lorde for the execution thereof. They who thinke the eſſence of a magiſtrate, any more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the gifts of courage, vnderſtanding, wiſdome, fearing God, dealing trulie,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod 18.21. deut. 1.13.</note> hating couetouſnes, (the onely properties mentioned by Iethro, whence
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:181007:27"/>this life of a magiſtrate is falſely gathered) then the being of a miniſter is contained in his<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.7.</note> faithfulnes, verie inconſiderately gaine-ſay the Apoſtle Peter in the place before quoted, becauſe hereby they make the magiſtracie not to bee an humaine ordinaunce, but an eccleſiaſticall conſtitution, preſcribed in the word. The obiection therefore that a miniſter ſhold be no more denied to be a miniſter, bicauſe he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth gifts, then a magiſtrate denied to bee a magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, for the ſame defect prooueth not woorth the anſwering. Becauſe the Lorde hath tied a mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herytance, no otherwaies vnto him, then hee hath the magiſtracie vnto that perſon or perſons who haue aucthoritie to make a magiſtrate. So that the very magiſtracie, may bee deriued from him by the outwarde calling, as well as the ſubſtantiall intereſt of this inheritance, by the beſt conuaiaunce in law. No ſuch thing beeing tied vnto the Church, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a miniſter; Becauſe none can ſay they are in the poſſeſſion of a miniſterie, who haue not the ſame from the Lord. And what miniſterie haue our readers from him? Any outward thing in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of man: (of which nature all men knowe the magiſtracie to be:) may bee conuaied really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, (ought not alwaies I graunt) vnto him vppon whomſoeuer man the poſſeſſour thereof will confer the ſame, and there it ought to be inuiolablie inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, as long as man whoſe right it is to beſtow it, or take it away, wil haue it ſo. Hath a man leſſe intereſt in his money, becauſe, either for want of witte, hee knoweth not how to vſe, or by his leudnes dooth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it? Candanles a foole, is no leſſe a magiſtrate, (a far worſe I deny not) among the Lydians,<note place="margin">Herod. lib. 1. Plato de reip. dial. 2.</note> then E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſilaus among the Lacedemonians, a wiſe and a politike gouernor. The ſame is to be ſaid of Ioab &amp;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:181007:28"/>Benaiah, of Licinius, a perſecutour and Conſtantine a chriſtan emperor. Tib. Ghracchus abuſeth his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, the ſenate and people ſin, becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him not, but as long as they tollerat him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the magiſtracie is his owne, and therefore not lawfull for any priuate man by diſobedience to rob him thereof. And why ſo? Becauſe the ſwoorde in his hand, is ſtill the Lords ſword, the ſedition &amp; ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie in him is his owne. To come to the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the Church maketh that wretch a miniſter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom it will be ſaid, I<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 7.22.23.</note> know thee not, thou wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of iniquitie. But did the Lorde by enduing him with graces meete for the miniſterie, ſay vnto him go propheſie in my name? hee did. Then there is a miniſterie committed vnto him, which is, neither his, nor the churches, but the Lordes, the ſame dare not I denie (vntill the Lorde take it awaye) for the foulnes of his handes. Another commeth with the ſame calling of the church, &amp; he ſayth b I am a plain heardman,<note place="margin">a Zachary. 13.5.</note> neither prophet, nor the ſonne of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. (Now Lord if it be thy will, bee mercifull vnto them, conuert them, and disburden thy church of them) but I haue my letters of orders from the Lord biſhop, and am in poſſeſſion of the liuing; I knowe no miniſterie he hath. And therefore I denie him to be any more a miniſter for his outward calling ſake, there Herdonius a traiterous and ſlauiſh ſeruant is a magiſtrate, though by treacherie, he with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of other rogiſh vagabonds like him ſelfe, hath now gotten poſſeſſion of the Capitol. That the ſpech may not ſeeme ſtraunge vnto any, let men way but the prerogatiue which the Lord reſerueth vnto him ſelfe, in making miniſters in hys Church: with the priuilege, which hir Maieſtie hath in ordaining ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates within hir dominions. The whole aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:181007:28"/>of Parliament for ſome cauſes mouing them, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a Lord high Conſtable of England, (as France hath) hir Maieſtie ſheweth hir publik diſliking ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And that ſhee will hauen) ſuch officer within hir Realme, is he a magiſtrate? hee is none neither wil I acknowledge him for any, as long as it ſhalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hir wil &amp; pleaſure to haue any ſuch within hir dominions. For what magiſtrate is he in this land, which ſhe ſaith to be none as long as the royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue is in hir hand. In like maner, what miniſter is he in the Church of God, whome the Lord deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be any. The caſe is too to manifeſt.</p>
            <p>The diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that readers are miniſters of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (that is ſent of the Lorde in iudgement to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſinnes in this age) but not miniſters of the mercie and grace of God, is as if they were ſayd to be miniſters of an ordinance neuer ordayned: now farre be it we ſhoulde make a miniſtery of an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance neuer reuealed, of an ordinaunce that is but temporary. And in very deed I cannot but thinke it a very ſtrange matter, that theſe men who make a conſcience of that which they teach, being alſo wiſe and godly learned, are not aſhamed to be reported the forgers and ſetters abroach of ſuch ſhifting and ſiely ſtuffe. The other obiection concerning the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery vnder Moſes, is as faultie For to ſquare the miniſterie of the new couenant, according vnto the Leuitical prieſthood, is to require the Conſulſhip of Rome, to be framed after the Maioraltie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, beſides manye other foule inconſequentes it hath in it. I haue alreadie ſhewed the weaknes her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and if it deſerued a further aunſweare, I woulde vouchſafe it the ſame.</p>
            <p>The reaſons expreſſed in the booke, are now to be ſet downe. Such of them as are noted with this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:181007:29"/>marke,<note place="margin">The thinges which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſeeke, I imbrace, their ſeperation I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</note> * are ſome of the reaſons, whereby I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily induced, vtterly to condemne that courſe of thoſe (I hope fearing God) who haue made a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from thoſe miniſters in this lande (&amp; their congregations) who truely preache the worde. And although there bee in our godly aſſemblies manye corruptions, and more wants tollerated, whiche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian heart muſt needs abhorre: yet I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that I would (as to my comfort I doe) ioyne my ſelfe in the publike hearing of the worde, receiuing of the ſacraments, praying, faſting, giuing of almes, and other holy exerciſes, which theſe congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as the aſſemblies of Gods people, amongſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> publike ſaluation is to be had, and with theſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as the meſſengers of Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from him, to make known vnto me the way of ſaluation, I dare not deny for my ſoule becauſe there is ſome want in the ſeale, I mean the outward calling. My reaſons are theſe; Where I am obſcure, the booke may giue light. The concluſion for breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake I haue omitted in the moſt. The Proſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme or ſecond proof of any doutfull action where it is omitted, is afterwarde concluded in the ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, which ſerueth for a proofe of all my reaſons, where any of them might be thought to be weake.</p>
            <p>Euery one that hath the * life of a miniſter good or bad (or that is a miniſter in deede) is ordained of God for the gathering<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12.3. 1. Cor. 4.11.28. Epheſ. 4.12.</note> together of the ſaintes. For ther is no other miniſter ſpoken of in the word. No bare reader is ordained of God for this end. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no bare reader is a miniſter in deede, or hath the life of a miniſter good or bad. The faithfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in the Church of England haue and do ſhewe by the good euidence of their teachinge, whereby ſoules are gathered vnto the church, and fed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:181007:29"/>that they were ordained of God for this ende. Therefore the ſeperation from them and their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, is an vngodly, wicked, and ſciſmatical rent from the viſible body of the churche. An vngodly, wicked, and ſciſmaticall rent, I call it vpon good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation &amp; aduice. Becauſe that ſeperation from the companye where publike ſaluation is had and profeſſed, which is made in ſuch ſort, as if the ſayde company had not the means of ſaluation ſounding in it, or worſhipped God after a falſe maner is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſciſmaticall. Such is the rent of theſe men. For as they themſelues do anouch, they are ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from vs, becauſe in all our meetings the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſo great, that we ſerue the true God after a falſe maner, hold not the foundation, and ſo haue no meanes to be ſaued among vs. For the men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, I hope the Lorde will recall them, and I am perſwaded the moſt of them haue fallen into this ſnare of meare and ſimple ignorance. And woe, woe woe (vnleſſe they repent) will be vnto them, that in ſmiting and keeping backe the carefull and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſheapheardes, haue beene the cauſe of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable diſperſion &amp; ſtraying of the poore ſheep. For the courſe, whiche they take in ſeekinge good things it is to be auoyded, as a courſe very likely to ſhake them from eternall life that continue in it. I know what I ſay. For where is there now any more meanes left for them to be ſaued without their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce (we hauing the onely ordinarie meanes of ſaluation among vs, as before is prooued) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they ſeperate themſelues from vs, as from thoſe who ſerue the true God after a falſe maner, and plainly ſhew that they would haue no ſaluation ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that whereof wee are by the mercies of God pertakers, through the miniſtery of the worde
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:181007:30"/>in our aſſemblies. They cannot deny (&amp; I deſire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to grant no more then the reaſons folowing, &amp; the former proue in this point) but that ſaluation is to be had by the miniſtery of our preachers. And they alſo know that there is but one ordinary way to be ſaued, which being accounted but in one aſſembly to be the way of ſeruing God after a falſe manner, the paſſage of ſaluation is ſhut vp euery where, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are thus ſeduced, for any thing that I know to be reuealed. Shall I becauſe the churche-gouernement is not as yet eſtabliſhed<note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> in Creta, or is iniuriouſly kept out, and ſome great corruptions tollerated in ſteade thereof, therefore affirme that thoſe congregations of the Cretians, where the word of god is taught by men of fit gifts; are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies where the true god is worſhipped after a falſe manner, and yet notwithſtanding thinke I may be ſaued by the worde preached at Philippi (continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill in the ſame error.) Whereas they that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the worde at Creta, are men endued with as rare gifts from the Lorde, for the worke of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, as vpright in life, and haue called as many to ſaluation, as they had done who are at Philippi. I doubt hereof. Naye, if I ſeperate my ſelfe from the aſſemblies in Creta, to go to Philippi, it ſhall not be becauſe I deny them to be meetings of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, among whome he ruleth by the ſcepter of the worde, or becauſe I account them prophane ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogs, but becauſe I ſee them too ſlacke in growing to that perfection, whereunto they deſire to bee brought, ſo that my departing ſhall not be a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a going forwarde. And while I addreſſe my ſelfe to goe forwarde, I will be ſure not to cut of my ſelfe, from the publike meetinges where the worde preached is inioyned. A ſtrong maner of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:181007:30"/>for men to cutte them-ſelues off, from the true Churche, to the ende they may haue a perfect out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gouernment. The practize of theſe ſilly men might ſeeme to be more tollerable, if they had ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues with any Churche vnder heauen. Nay, I would ſee what church dareth receiue them as long as they holde theſe congregations for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous ſynagogs, where that ordinance of God is, by which men are brought out of the kingdome of darknes vnto the kingdome of Chriſt. Euery one of the ſyllogiſmes noted with this marke, * inferre the former concluſion againſt their practize. I wiſhe their conuerſion from my heart, and will be readie to performe any chriſtian duetie (as a brother) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that the Lord hath enabled me.</p>
            <p>Euery miniſter<note n="(2)" place="margin">2</note> indeed * of that ordinaunce<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13.</note> which is to continue in the church, for the worke of the miniſterie to the worlds end. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Noe bare reader is a miniſter of this ordinance. For this ordinance is the woord preached. Ergo no bare reader is a miniſter indeed.<note n="(3)" place="margin">3</note> Euery miniſter is able * to make the elect to be members of<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13.</note> Chriſt. No bare reader is ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument. Ergo;<note n="(4)" place="margin">4</note> Euerie miniſter * is a meanes by the worde of the grace of God to giue the elect an inheritaunce among them that are<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> ſanctified. None of our readers is ſuch a meanes, ergo:<note n="(5)" place="margin">5</note> Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie miniſter indeede, is able to feed the * elect with the food of knowledge and<note n="d" place="margin">Iere. 3.15.</note> vnderſtanding. None of our bare readers are able to do this: ergo:<note n="(6)" place="margin">6</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie * miniſter at the leaſt, in regard of gifts, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the Lords owne<note n="e" place="margin">Ierem. 3.15.</note> heart, that is, his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance reuciled concerning his * choice. None of our readers is ſuch: ergo:<note n="(7)" place="margin">7</note> Euery miniſter is * an inſtrument to make knowen by the word preached,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:181007:31"/>the purpoſe<note n="a" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.20.23 28.</note> of God concerning mans reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. No reder is ſuch: ergo:<note n="(8)" place="margin">8</note> Euery miniſter is able to lay open * the myſteries of ſaluation. No reader is &amp;c:<note place="margin">Looke this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the book.</note> ergo:<note n="(9)" place="margin">9</note> Euery miniſter is an * inſtrument of our new<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.21.</note> birth. No bare reader is &amp;c: ergo:<note n="(10)" place="margin">10</note> Euerie miniſter is able by the preaching of the Goſpell. to manifeſt thoſe hidden ſecreats, whiche the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets them-ſelues could not artaine vnto,<note place="margin">1, Pet, 1.10.12.</note> without great ſearch and enquirie. No bare reader can doo this by preaching: ergo:<note n="(11)" place="margin">11</note> Euery miniſter is * a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by his publike miniſtery, to bring the elect vnto the knowledge of the truth and ſo to ſaluation.<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4.</note> No bare reader can doe this: ergo:<note n="(12)" place="margin">12</note> Whoſoeuer are fit in regard of their ſufficiencie to bee their miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters alone, that would haue no God,<note n="d" place="margin">2. Chron. 15.3.</note> are no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters indeede. All bare readers, not beeing able to lay open the will of the true God, are onely fit to bee their miniſters that would haue no God: ergo: they are no miniſters indeede.<note n="(13)" place="margin">13</note> They are no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, whoſoeuer are able to performe the whole worke of their miniſterie without ſtudie, and giuing heed vnto learning, as the<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.14.14.</note> apoſtle commandeth. But all our readers (if they can read) can performe the whole work of their calling, as long as they liue, without any further ſtudye: ergo: they are no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters indeed<note n="14" place="margin">14</note>. Euery miniſter * is able to expound that which<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 8.13.14.</note> cannot be vnderſtoode without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretour, viz, that, which is to be learned out of the word concerning the Lorde, &amp; mans ſaluation. Our bare readers cannot do this: ergo:<note n="15" place="margin">15</note>. Euerie miniſter * is a miniſter of that waye, whereby the Lord beſtoweth vpon men the ſpirite of wiſedome, and reuelation through his knowledge.<note n="g" place="margin">Eze. 2.17:</note> Our bare readers are not ſuch: ergo:<note n="16" place="margin">16</note>. Euery * miniſter is able to make the word of God powerfull, either vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:181007:31"/>to death or vnto life, in<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 4 12.2. 2. chro. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſome of the hearers. Our readers are not able to doe this: ergo: 17 Euerye miniſter is * able to deuide the word of God aright<note place="margin">12</note> vnto the ſeuerall vſe of the hearers.<note n="b" place="margin">2. Tim 1.10. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ. 1.5.7.</note> Our readers are not able to do this: ergo:<note place="margin">18</note> 18 Euery miniſter is able to tech thoſe that can read,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.22. &amp; 3.10.</note> as wel as himſelf. No bare reader can do this: ergo:<note place="margin">19</note> 19 Euery mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter can doe ſome thing in regarde of teaching his flocke, which euery chriſtian, who can read well &amp; diſtinctly, is not able to performe. Our readers can not do this: ergo:<note place="margin">20</note> 20 whoſoeuer by naturall gifts alone, are able to performe, whatſoeuer belongeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their<note n="d" place="margin">Rom 7.7. &amp; 12.3. ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.8. 1. coa. 3.10. &amp; 4.7. heb. 5.4. epheſ. 4.7.</note> calling they are no miniſters, bicauſe there is ſome thing (to ſpeak the leaſt) in the miniſtry of euery miniſter whiche cannot poſtiblie bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by natural gifts alone. Our readers are able by the onely gifts of nature, to perfourme whatſoeuer belong vnto their calling, ergo: our readers are no miniſters indeed.<note place="margin">21</note> 21 Euery miniſter * hath gifts to labour in Gods husbandrie, and Gods building:<note place="margin">22</note> 1. Cor. 3.8. 1. Theſ. 5.2. our readers haue not: ergo: 22 Euerye * miniſter hath neceſſarily annexed, vnto his calling, workes of that admiration, that it maye bee truly ſayd of them, who is fit for theſe things. 2. Cor. 2.16. our readers are not: ergo:<note place="margin">23</note> 23. Euerye miniſter is able to make the Lord ſo knowen to the elect, that they dare call vpon him, in ſaith and full perſwaſion to be hard. Rom. 10.14. &amp; 8.15. our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders cannot do this: ergo: 24. Euerie miniſter is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall things,<note place="margin">24</note> and to ſpeake the worde<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 2 13. 1. theſ 4.11.</note> of GOD, as the word of God: our readers are not able to doe this ergo:<note place="margin">25</note> 25 Whoſoeuer preſerueth * not knowledge in his lips, that is, wanteth the thing, the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>whereof, in a priuate man, not beeing cenſurable by the church,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:181007:32"/>viz. not being a ſin in it ſelfe, giueth the Lord &amp; the church iuſt cauſe, both to keep them from the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, and to expell them out of the miniſtery, in whome this want is found, though they bee euerye way els qualified for the miniſtery, according vnto the<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir. 1.6.7. 1. cor. 4.2.1. theſ. 2.2.11</note> proprieties required in the word, hee is no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. Our readers haue this wante in them: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their lips doe not preſerue knowledge: ergo, they are no miniſters indeed. Thus my reaſon is in the booke page 8. drawen out of Mala. 2.7. is to bee concluded. For although a man want all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties of a miniſter, yet being fit to teach, he hath ſome allowaunce from the Lorde to bee a miniſter, whereas the want heere of kepeth back the Lordes whole conſent, from the admiſſion of him into the miniſterie, in whom it is.</p>
            <p>The reaſon whereof is, that all other proprieties in a miniſter, ſauing this, are ſuch, as according to the ordinance of God, ought to be in euery chriſtian (as to be modeſt, harberous, no ſtriker, &amp;c.) as well as in the miniſter, though not in the ſame meaſute, this by the Lords inſtitution, is to be in the miniſter one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of neceſſitie: howbeit other chriſtians alſo may be and are capable thereof.<note place="margin">26</note> 26 Whoſoeuer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goeth that miniſtery,<note place="margin">Looke the book page 8.</note> and no other, whereof a Turk, Painime, or Iewe, who will not learne true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may be capable, he in deede is no miniſter. Our readers vndergoe no other miniſterie;<note place="margin">27</note> &amp;c. ergo. 27 They whoſe miniſtery make the whole religion of chriſtians, not to haue in it, ſo much as one myſtery, (the ſecrecie whereof euen in regard of knowledge, might diſable one, that neuer heard of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a publike miniſter thereof) are no miniſters in deede. The miniſterye of all bare readers is ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ergo,<note place="margin">28</note> 28 They are no miniſters, who for their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:181007:32"/>alone, call for the wrath of God vpon the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern ours and the land, where they are tollerated: our readers though otherwiſe the holieſt men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen call, &amp;c, ergo. 29 All miniſters * maye truely ſay of themſelues,<note place="margin">19 2. Cor. 5.20.</note> now then are we ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours from Chriſte, as though God did beſeeche you through vs, we pray you in Chriſts ſteade, that you be reconciled vnto God: Our readers cannot truely ſay, &amp;c: ergo. 30 Euery one that is a miniſter in deed, hath more in him, then parents,<note place="margin">30 Look the book page 9.</note> both vnder the law, and vnder the Goſpell, were and are bound to haue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who though they neither coulde nor can read, were and are bounde to reach their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: our readers haue not thus much:<note place="margin">31 Looke page 10.</note> ergo. 31 E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery miniſter * is a miniſter of the wholſom doctrine ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, 2, Tim. 4, 3: our readers are not: ergo. 32 Euery miniſter, * in what age ſoeuer he liueth,<note place="margin">32 Coloſ. 13.29.</note> is able to bring the electe (who are borne citizens of darknes, vnto the kingdome of Chriſte: our readers cannot do this: ergo.<note place="margin">33</note> 33 Euerye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is able by the word preached, to cut of the buds that ſpring, out of the roote of corruptions, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the regenerate: Our readers are not: ergo, 34 Euery miniſter * is able to make the food of life, to be milke vnto the weak,<note place="margin">34 b 1. Cor. 3.2. heb 5.14</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſtrong meat to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are capable thereof: our readers are not: ergo. 35 Euery miniſter * is able to make cleare vnto the elect, what the fellowſhip is, of the miſterie,<note place="margin">35</note> whiche b from the beginning of the world hath bene hid in God: our readers are not:<note place="margin">c Ephe 3.9.</note> ergo.<note place="margin">36 Looke page 11.</note> 36 They who are miniſters * of thoſe viſions alone, that cannot turne the people from iniquitie, nor diſcouer ſinner, are no miniſters in deed: our readers are ſuch: ergo.<note place="margin">37</note> 37 The * people liuinge vnder them that are miniſters in deed, may hope for eternall life by their miniſterie,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:181007:33"/>if they faithfully execute the ſame: But the people liuing vnder our readers, though they faithfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute their miniſterie, cannot hope: ergo. 38 Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie * miniſter is a miniſter of the waye,<note place="margin">38</note> whereby the Lord ordained, he ſhould be publikely ſerued of his people, and they trained vp in his feare: our readers are not: ergo. 39 They are no miniſters * whoſe flockes the Lord may purſue,<note place="margin">39</note> with his eternal curſe, for contenting them-ſelues with their miniſterie, though they faithfully diſcharge, whatſoeuer by their outwarde calling is enioyned them: But the flocks of our readers are ſuch as, &amp;c: ergo. 40 They * are no miniſters,<note place="margin">40</note> whoſe flocks by their miniſterye, cannot ſanctifie the Sabboth: our readers are ſuch: ergo.<note place="margin">41</note> 41 They * are no miniſters in deed, that haue not gifts to obey Paules charge: Our readers haue not:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1.2.</note> ergo.<note place="margin">42</note> 42 They are no miniſters in deede, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer may truely ſay of themſelues, truely wee are no miniſters in deed, b though we haue an outwarde calling:<note n="a" place="margin">Zach. 3.5.</note> our readers may truely ſay thus: ergo. 43 They who are in the eſtate of damnation for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in the miniſtery,<note place="margin">43.</note> though they be guiltie of no other notorious ſinne, are no miniſters: Suche are our readers: ergo. 44 They are no miniſters, whoſe congregations hauing no other miniſtry,<note place="margin">44</note> ſince they haue bene Idolatrous ſynagogs, can neuer by their miniſtery be ſaid to haue the outward<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 28.18.19. ephEſ. 1.13. col. 2.11.17. Looke page 24.25.</note> markes of a true Church: But the congregations of our readers are ſuch: ergo. 45 They that are * miniſters in deed, do not ſinne becauſe they do adminiſter the ſacraments: But our readers (as all the godly confeſſe) ſin in preſuming to deal with any action belonging vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a miniſter,<note place="margin">45</note> and therfore the ſacraments: ergo. All theſe reaſons, beſides the other ſyllogiſtically ſette down, where I deale with the prophanation of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:181007:33"/>by our readers, are expreſſed in the booke. Now that euery one of theſe ſeuerally, &amp; all iointly are of themſelues alone (none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> depending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the proofe, that is gotten by the other) ſeuerall, and ioynt demonſtrations, concluding our readers to be no miniſters, I thus prooue.</p>
            <p>All theſe reaſons whereof euery one ſeuerally &amp; all ioyntly, do conclude them to be no miniſters in deede, who are not preaching miniſters, they alſo conclude our readers to be no miniſters. But all the former reaſons (or the moſt of them) conclude the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be no miniſters in deed, which are not preachers, (by preachers; I mean not euery one that can ſpeak for an houre in the pulpit, but ſuch in deed, as ſhew b by the enidence of their reaching,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.14. epheſ. 4.12. gal. 3.1.2. cor. 10.4. 1. theſ. 1.5.</note> that they are ordained of God, for the gathering togither of the Saints) therefore alſo they conclude our readers to be no miniſters indeed: Vnto the former I ad theſe.<note place="margin">46</note> 46 The calling * of euerye one thot is a miniſter in deed, is a ſanctified calling in it ſelfe, to him that is thereunto called, and hath giftes to diſcharge the ſame. But the very calling, (I do not ſay popedomes, archbiſhopriks, pride, couetouſnes, epicuriſm, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, &amp; wretched ignorance, Lording ouer others, oppoſing themſelues to the Lord Ieſus and his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) of our readers, is an vngodly, and vnſanctified vocation, to bee a calling of the miniſtery, becauſe there is no ſuche miniſterie as they vndergoe, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the worde: ergo, they are no miniſters in deed.<note place="margin">47</note> 47 Their * calling is no calling of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and ſo they no miniſters: for the remouing of whoſe miniſterie, it is<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 9.38.</note> lawfull * for vs to pray: But it is lawfull to pray for the remoouing of this dumb miniſtery out of the Church: ergo.<note place="margin">48</note> 48 They * are no miniſters, who may betake themſelues without
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:181007:34"/>ſinne, to another calling, when the Churche wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth miniſters, eſpecially if they may exerciſe their miniſterie in peace, Our readers may: ergo. 49 E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery * one that is a miniſter,<note place="margin">44</note> hath that calling vpon him, whereunto the Lorde according vnto his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance b committeth the charge of ſoules: our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders haue no ſuch calling: ergo. 50 Euery miniſter * hauing a flocke committed vnto him may be,<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Doctor or the Paſtor thereof:<note place="margin">50</note> Our readers can be neither: ergo.<note place="margin">51</note> 51 The birth of that which, was neuer conceiued, is no birthe in deede. But our readers are birthes that were neuer conceiued, that is, miniſters by their outward ordination, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they neuer had any conception, that is, inwarde calling:<note place="margin">52</note> ergo. 52 They * are no miniſters, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whoſe triall, there bee no rules ſet downe<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 22. &amp; 3.10.</note> in the word: Such are our readers: ergo. 53 They are no miniſters, the eſſentiall worke of whoſe ſuppoſed miniſterie, may bee performed according vnto the ordinance of God, by thoſe, who both haue a func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diuers from the calling of theſe readers, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, without offence vnto Gods children, ſuch a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, as ignorant readers take vpon them. This propoſition is moſt true, becauſe there is but one fort of miniſters, namely, the ordinance of God, and not of the Church mentioned in the word: But our readers are ſuch, as the eſſentiall work of their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed calling, being the works of a miniſter in deed, may according to the ordinance of God, be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by thoſe, who both haue a function diuers from (yea, contrarie to) theſe readers function, as good is to euill, vz. by preachers, whoſe calling being a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified calling, muſt needes be in nature, not onely diuers from, but contrarie to, the caling of readers, which is not warranted by the worde, a calling war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:181007:34"/>and a calling not warranted being contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and deteſt without offence vnto Gods children, ſuch a miniſterie, as dumb readers take vpon them. Therefore our bare readers though they haue the name and ſupplie the place of miniſters, are not miniſters in deed: And not being in deed miniſters, it is not left vnto me as a thing indifferent by chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie, whether I will communicate with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or no: Becauſe that of neceſſity, I am bound to com for the ſacraments, vnto the ordinaunce of<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 21.25. &amp; 11.11. 1. cor. 12.4.11.</note> God, that is, vnto a miniſter: and not vnto the ordinance of the church, neither haue I any liberty to attempt the contrarie. And as before hath bene prooued, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery miniſter is the ordinaunce of<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 12.5.28 epheſ. 4.7.11.</note> God, &amp; not the ordinance of the Church, ordained when our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſte led captiuitie<note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.8. math. 28.19.</note> captiue, and not ſince. Nowe our readers being but the ordinance of the Church, ordained ſince that time, and the Church hauing no libertie to ordaine ſacramentes: I haue alſo no libertie, no not in the time of neceſſitie, to come vnto the ordinance of the Church for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes: becauſe there I can haue no more, for any thing I know, then the Church whence the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance is, hath power to giue. And I pray you what ſacrament is that, which the bare ordinance of the Church can deliuer?</p>
            <p>Theſe be ſome of the reaſons, (and I take no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the nomber of them) wherevpon, as on the infallible trueth of Gods ſacred word, I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude the moſt within wales, ſupplying the places of miniſters, to be no miniſters in deed, and to haue nothing in them, that giueth life vnto a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, good or bad. And therevpon I dare as boldly affirme the courſe to bee a wicked and ſiſmatticall courſe, which they take, that ſeperate them ſelues
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:181007:35"/>from the publike aſſemblies, where the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched is truly taught in this land, as from thoſe who ſerue the true God, after a falſe maner. In the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of whiche reaſons, I proteſt with a good conſcience, that I haue ſo laboured, both at the firſt edition of the booke, (ſome reaſons then moouing me to deale more timorouſlie in the action) &amp; ſince that time eſpecialle, as I haue not ſuffered my ſelfe to be deceiued by any ſophiſme, or fallation. And I proreſt before the Lord, that vpon theſe grounds, I both aſſuredly know their courſe, (of whome I haue ſpoken, to be dangerous and deteſtable, and am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as ſurely perſwaded, that menne not ordained of God for the gathering of the ſaints, are no miniſters whatſoeuer calling they haue in the Church, as I beleeue the bleſſed apoſtle Paule to haue beene an apoſtle ſent from God. And bicauſe I am one daye to bee reckonad with, before the iudgement ſeat of Ieſus Chriſte, of my ſinceare dealing in both thoſe points, and liue now in the church of God, the leaſt member whereof; Woe be vnto me if I offende, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo I liue vnder hir highnes a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, whoſe ſacred ancthoritie I ſubiect my ſelfe vnto, &amp; reuerence as the royall ordinance of gods owne maieſtie, and whoſe poſitiue lawes and procc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, as far as I may with a good conſcience tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate their imperfections, I dare not gain-ſaye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe likewiſe, what I haue written, ſhalbe recorded and called in queſtion in the church of God, (when I am gone the way of all fleſh) vnto whome I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide to commend my name, as a brocher of newe doctrines: therefore I haue beene carefull to ſette down nothing, but that which will abide the triall of all whoſoeuer, and abide firme againſt all. If any of my godly, teuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; lerned brethren of the church
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:181007:35"/>of Englande, will doe me the fauour (which thing I earneſtly requeſt at their hands) in ſhort ſyllogiſms to communicate with mee in writing, their reaſons for the miniſterie of theſe ignoraunt men. I ſhall haue cauſe to praiſe the Lord, and thanke them for their loue towards me in this point alſo, and the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier ſatisfie whatſoeuer may be ſayd on the behalf of this vnlearned (I woulde vnknowen) miniſterie. I greatlye reuerence many godlye and learned, that are contrary minded vnto me in this cauſe; I know my yeares to bee ſubiect vnto that bolde temerity, hoat, and heady raſhnes, which bleſſed Timothy in<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.22.</note> conſideration of his age, was bidden by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to auoide: notwithſtanding, in regarde of the cauſe (in humilitie before the Lord, his elect angels and children bee it ſpoken) I may iuſtly (for beit I ſhould) contemne and deſpiſe, almoſt not vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to anſwer, whatſoeuer man or angell, can bring againſt it. And I dare areſt and attaint, of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the maieſtie of the higheſt all thoſe, both men and aungels, who either defend the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with them lawfull; communicate with them, or tollerate them as miniſters vnder their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_council">
            <head>TO THE LL. OF THE COVNSEL.</head>
            <p>ANd for aſmuch, as both in this place, for tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating the dumb miniſterie, and in the book page. 36, for ſuffering non-reſidents, and the papall Lordſhips of our 4. L. Bb. in Wales, I affirm our gouerriours to be guiltie of fearefull ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Maieſtie of God, I am with all the humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, reuerence and ſubmiſſion, my heart can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, to vſe a ſpeach vnto your HH. my Lordes of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:181007:36"/>her maieſties priuy Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel. The cauſe that moueth me heerevnto, is, the diſcharge of my dutie towards the Lorde my God, towards his Church, towardes my natiue Countrey, and towardes your Honours, which could not ſtand with my ſilence in this point: concerning the Lord, becauſe I am a poore wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinner, vppon whome he hath ſhewed great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in calling mee to the knowledge of his ſon, and pardoning my dreadfull ſinnes; I haue taken a bond of my ſelfe by his grace, to be come an enemy vnto ſinne, in my ſelfe eſpecially, and in all others as far as my calling will permitte, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, time, place, eſtate or condicion of life whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. And therfore your Hh. are not to marueile, if I ſeeke the ouerthrowe of theſe places, callings, and corruptions (L. Biſhops, readers and non-reſidents I mean) whoſe continuance ſtandeth with the lords moſt notable diſhonour, and deteſt ſinne euen in your Hh. whoſe aucthority, good name, credit, eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and high places (next vnto her royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties) I ought, and by the grace of God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, againſt all the detractours there of, with the loſſe of my life, when it ſhall be needfull. As for the Church of God: wherevnto I haue bene begotten, through the word preached, by means of my abode in Englande, in theſe peaceable dayes of her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I haue wholye dedicated my ſelfe to ſeeke the flowriſhing eſtate thereof. By labouring to beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame, both in the plucking vp of thoſe filthie Italian weeds, wherewith now it is miſerablie defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and planting therein, whatſoeuer may bee to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lines of gods orchard. For my pore country, becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord of life, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I firſt ſaw the light of the ſon, and haue beene by my parents there liuing, brought vp in both the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:181007:36"/>of this land, I haue vowed my ſelfe duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to benefite the ſame, whether by my life or by my death, I do not greatly weye.</p>
            <p>And wherein ſhall I ſtand my deare countrimen in any ſtead, if not by ſpeakinge in their cauſe, that are not able to make knowne their owne wantes. If not in bleſſing the deafe eares, in remouing the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blingblock from before the eyes of the blind, if not in labouring to bring them to heauen, who of their owne natures ſhould liue eternally in a worſe place to their own wo. The aforenamed callings and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, ſtanding as enemies in the way to hinder my brethren from eternall life; I profeſſe my ſelfe to ſeeke their ouerthrowe and confuſion: And by the Lordes aſſiſtance, as longe as I liue I will neuer leaue them, vnles they leaue the maſſakring of the ſoules of my brethren. In reſpect of your HH. ſeinge I receiued the former bleſſings throgh your hands, by meanes of the outward peace, whereof her right excellent Maieſtie hath made the whole kingdome partaker from the Lord; I canot of conſcience, but in moſt ſubmiſſ. reuerend, and humble ſort, put you in minde, of the eſtate wherein you ſtand before the Lord at this day.</p>
            <p>I affirme therefore (and I would to God I coulde tell howe, more dutifully to expreſſe in wordes, that whiche in heart I haue moſt dutifully conceiued) that all of you are in a feareful manner, both in this life, and in that to come ſubiect, to the intollerable maſle of Gods wrath, the execution whereof, ſhall vndoubtedly come vpon you and your houſes, vnles you preuent the fiercenes of his indignation: And that for theſe 2. cauſes. Firſt, inaſmuch as the whole countrie of Wales for the moſt part, all this time of the Goſpell in England, hath bene without the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:181007:37"/>ſeruice of God, in the publike meetings of your people, in ſuch ſort, as moſt parriſhes within Wales haue wanted the means of ſaluation all this time of your gouernement. The trueth of this aſſertion is manifeſted in this little booke (becauſe they haue wanted<note n="a" place="margin">Ia. 2.21: 1. pet. 1.25. Iob. 33.23. 1. cor. 1.21. rom. 10.14 eph. 1.13. &amp; 2.17. act. 20.32 prou. 8.34.35. iſai. 53.11.</note> preaching) and I haue elſwher to my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er laboured to make it known vnto her Maieſtie, &amp; the parliament. Conſider my Lordes, what care you haue had of the ſoules of men, and howe in the day of account theſe things will be anſwered: Conſider how lamentable a caſe it is, that in the flowriſhingſt gouernment for outwarde peace, that is againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the coape of heauen, where publicke idolatrie hath bene banniſhed, not one familie, or one tribe, but a whole nation ſhould periſh and be deſtroyed for want of knowledge. And ſee whether I haue not ſufficient cauſe to deale with you, in the behalfe of my countrimen. My crie, my crie, is not the crie of guiltles and innocent a blood,<note place="margin">b Deut. 21.8.</note> which were verie wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but of loſt and damned ſoules which is moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, &amp; giue eare vnto it my LL. leſt the blood of ſoules be laid to your charge, &amp; required at your hands. If I be thoght to report an vntruth, in regard of the eſtate of the Church in my countrie, let me bee brought face to face for the triall hereof, with thoſe vnto whom the care (I ſhould ſay the ſpoile) of the Church there is committed, and being conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to haue vttered an vntrueth, let me haue no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, but die the death, before your Honours, and my blood bee vppon mine owne head, for impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the credit of the princes of my people, vndu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifullie by publike writing, whoſe eſtimation, I know it to be vnlawfull for mee, euen in thought once to violate. I do here therefore before your HH. offer to proue, that the moſt congregations in Wales, want
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:181007:37"/>the verie eſſential outward marks of a true church, and ſo the meanes of ſaluation, and the comfort of faith, by the right adminiſtration of the ſacraments: I alſo offer to proue, that you ſhalbe reckoned with, without your ſpeedie repentaunce, becauſe that in this point you haue plowed but iniquitie and ſowed wickedneſſe, and ſo as Iob ſaith, you ſhall reape the ſame. Belieue them not that tell you all is well,<note place="margin">Iob. 4.8.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your gouernment in Wales, and that they are a ſort of clamorous and vndiſcreet men, that affirme the contrarie. Beleeue them not that tell you that it belongeth not vnto your dutie to be careful of the eſtate of the Church; &amp; that the Lord requireth no more at your hands, but to maintain outward peace As though men committed to your gouernement, were but droues of bruit beaſtes, onely to be fodde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and kept from externall inuaſions and inrodes: giue care rather vnto the woordes of the prophet, who with a loude voice, crieth vnto you, why will you die, you, your families,<note place="margin">Ierem. 27.23.14.</note> and your people by the ſword, by the famine, and by the peſtilence, and why wil you be damned, as the Lord hath ſpoken againſt (I may allude without iniurie to the word) all thoſe gouernours that will not<note n="a" place="margin">Ezra. 7.17.23. pſal. 2.10. &amp; 101 2. chro. 29.10. &amp; 30.9. &amp; 34.27. exod. 20.10. gen 18.19.2. chron. 15.12.13. &amp; 17.7</note> ſee their people proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the meanes of ſaluation. Therfore heare not the wordes of the Prophetes that tell you, you ſhall neither ſee ſworde, or famine, though you be ſtill as careles of your people, as you hytherto haue bene looke the puniſhement both of the flatteringe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and of thoſe that are deceiued by their flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Ierem. 14.16. Heare them not I ſay, but obey the Lorde in the execution of that dutie which he effla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitateth at your handes, by calling of your people vnto the knowledge of his ſonne, that you may liue for why ſhould this land bee made deſolate for this
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:181007:38"/>your careleſnes. Ier. 27.17. They propheſie vanity &amp; a lie vnto your HH. that ſaie peace, peace vnto you, while in this point you deſpiſe the Lorde, and walke ſtill in this ſecure courſe, or elſe<note n="a" place="margin">Iere. 23.16.17.</note> Ieremie is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if they be prophets. And if the word of the lord be in their mouthes,<note n="b" place="margin">Ierem. 27.18.</note> let them intreat the Lorde, her Maieſtie and your HH. (and ſtirre you vp to ſee) that the miſerie of helpleſſe Wales may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red off. You are in a miſerable taking, my LL, that either you haue none about you, to tell you of theſe things, or that men dare not tel you of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you are more miſerable if being warned of your eſtate, you be hardened ſtill in this ſecuritie. But this is not all.</p>
            <p>Secondly therefore, the Lords wrath hangeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your heads for tollerating in Wales the dumb miniſtery, the vſurped and Antichriſtian ſeates of Lorde Byſhops, and other Romiſh offices there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining and ſo tollerated, as by your conſente and authoritie they are in force. If Moſes by a poſitiue law, ſhould haue allowed the offring of ſtrange fire, by Nadab and Abihu, tollerated the miniſterie of<note n="c" place="margin">Leui: 20.18 23</note> blemiſhed and deformed Leuites, enacted that one not being of the line of Aaron, might preſſe before the Altar,<note n="d" place="margin">Nom. 16.10. &amp; 18.7.</note> to offer the breade of his God, if Dauid had made it lawfull for Huzza to lay his hand vpon the Arke, if Ioſiah or any of the godly rulers had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen leaue vnto the curſed ſhepherds in their daies, to place others in their ſteed<note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 44.8.</note> to take the ouerſight of the Sanctuarie, briefly had eſtabliſhed any thing contrary to the commandement, in the Churche-gouernment preſcribed by Moſes, had they not bin in danger of Gods wrath? queſtionles they had. And ſhal your HH. be diſpenced with, being guilty of tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating and eſtabliſhing greater thinges amongſt your people in Wales, in ſtead of the gouernement
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:181007:38"/>preſcribed by Ieſus Chriſt, aſſure your ſelues no. I do therefore in this point for the diſcharge of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and dutie towards the Lord, his church, my Countrey, and your Hh. taking my life in my hand, teſtifie vnto you before the eternall GOD and his church, that our vnlearned miniſterie is no miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in deede, that the calling of our L. Bb. Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Commiſſaries, ſomoners, and al other the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of the Romiſhe vomit, as non-reſidents, &amp;c, remaining in Wales, are intolerable before the Lorde: and that it is not likely that euer your Hh. tollerating theſe things any longer, ſhall eſcape the reuenging hand of God. The truth hereof, I make knowne briefly, (bicauſe I would not be tedious) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Hh. by the reaſons following, and offer to prooue theſe things more at large vppon the perill of my life, and by the grace of God will, againſt our 4. L. Bb. all their Chapleins, retainers, fauourers, and welwillers, whether in either of the two vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities in this lande, or in anye place els in earth, or in hell, for in heauen I knowe they haue no fautors. Theſe things I offer to prooue againſt D. Bridges, who lately in a booke of 7. ſhillings price, hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-taken their defence, wherein beſides the wrong done vnto the Church of God, he hath offered her Maieſtie and your Hh. moſt vndutifull iniurye, by going about<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the defence of his bellye, and the bellies of the reſt of his coate, to ouerthrowe her Maieſties title of ſoueraigne preheminence, and to alienate the heartes of the loyalleſt ſubiectes in the land, from their moſt louing and carefull Prince &amp; gouernours; As though her Maieſtie and your. Hh. ment to turne the edge of the ſword againſt them, who indeed deſerue not to be ſmitten with the ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard. And I will prooue, that he hath crammed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:181007:39"/>this gorge, as plaine poperie for the defence of our prelates: as euer Belarmin, Turrian, Harding, Saunders, or any other the fierbrands, and enſign-bearers of Romiſhe treaſon againſt her Maieſties crowne, haue brought for the title of the popes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy. Although he hath bene, and I doubt not ſhalbe ſufficiently anſwered, by thoſe, whoſe bookes hee is not worthie to beare, yet, in aſmuch as hee in this booke hath ſhewed him ſelfe to bee an Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh, Tobiah, againſt the building of Ieruſalem in Wales, by deſending (alaſſe) reliquias Danaum, the very breaches and ruines of the Babyloniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, which by the iuſt iudgement of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der poperie, we haue ſuſtained to be the perfecteſt building that Syon can be brought vnto, and ſo by this ſlaunder, withſtandeth the ſaluation (which I doubt not) her Maieſtie, and your Hh. wiſhe vnto my Countrey; I haue ſo framed my reaſons folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they ouerthrowe the verye foundation and whole frame of that wicked booke. And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion, that his cauſe maye falſ. If I (beſides that which others wil do (ouerthrow him, &amp; his cauſe, I offer before your Hh. to lie in irons, &amp; eat the bread of affliction, vntill in a twiſe 7. pennie booke I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue by the worde, make an vtter ſpoyle, ruine, &amp; ouerthrow, of whatſoeuer he hath brought for the defence of that, whiche in the gouernement, is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned according to the woorde, by the learned in this Lande. I ſpeake not more confidentlye then I ſhould do, for I know the cauſe to be a moſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſure cauſe, and therefore not timorouſlye to be dealt in, but in the feare of God, with all bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be ſtood too and aduouched.</p>
            <p>Nowe that our dumbe miniſters, non-reſidents, L. Bb. Arch-deacons &amp;c, are nothing els but an
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:181007:39"/>increaſe<note n="a" place="margin">Nom. 22.14.</note> of ſinfull men, riſen vppe in ſtead of their fathers the Idolatrous monks and fryers, ſtil to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the fierce wrath of God againſt this land, and you our gouernours, and that this booke of D. Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and whatſoeuer els hath bene written for their defence, are nothing els but edicts, traitors againſt God, and ſlaunderers to your ſacred gouernement, to defend the ſale and exchange of church goods, and the verye diſtruction of ſoules, to ſpeake all in a word, that both theſe cortuptions and their defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are condemded by the Lords reuealed will, as things directly againſt his will, and the lawes of his maieſtie expreſſed in his written word, and therfore not to be tollerated by your Hh. vnleſſe, you thinke you may tollerate ſinne by law, nor yet once to bee ſpoken for, or countenannced, vnleſſe you woulde plead for<note n="b" place="margin">Iudg. 6.31.</note> Baall, I prooue by theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>That forme of Church-gouernment; which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Ieſus Chriſt to bee inferiour vnto Moſes, is an vngodly gouernement, flat contrary to the<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 3.6. nom. 12, 7.</note> worde, and therefore in no caſe to bee tollerated, and the booke, or bookes defending the ſame, are vngodlye wicked, and lying bookes. But our Church-gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Wales, by L. Bb. Arch-deacons, dumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters, and other eccleſiaſtical officers there, (as for non-reſidents, let this one reaſon for all ſerue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they, in aſmuch as in them lyeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue the people, ouer whome they thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, of the onely ordinarye meanes to ſaluation, which is the<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 10.14. 1. cor. 1.21. 1. pet. 1.21.</note> word preached,) is ſuch a gouernment as maketh the Lord of life, Ieſus Chriſt inferior vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Moſes, and this book of Doctor Bridges doth the ſame, therfore this gouernement in a gouernement not to be tollerated by law in any ſtate, vnleſſe men would feele gods heauie iudgements for the ſame,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:181007:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:181007:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:181007:41"/>and therefore alſo a gouernement moſt pernitious and daungerous vnto the ciuill magiſtrate where it is eſtabliſhed, and this booke or bookes defending the ſame, are vngodly, wicked, and lying books, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous againſt the Maieſtie of Ieſus Chriſt, crying for the importable vengeaunce of God vppon ſuch Magiſtrates as tollerate them. The propoſition is not to be doubted off. The aſſumption is thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided. That gouernement, and that booke, whiche holdeth Ieſus Chriſt, God and man, to haue preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed no external form of gouernment in his church but ſuch as at the pleaſure of the magiſtrate, when time and place requireth, may without ſinne be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: preferreth Moſes before the Lord Ieſus: This is manifeſt out of the expreſſe word out of the text. Heb. 3.2.6. Becauſe that the Lorde Ieſus beeing the ſonne, in this place is compared with Moſes a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſeruaunt, is preferred before Moſes, in regarde of the externall gouernement, which Moſes had ſo faithfully preſcribed, as it was not to bee altered or chaunged at the pleaſure of any magiſtrate, vntill the meſſiah ſhould cauſe the oblations to ceaſ.<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 9, 27.</note> For whatking was there euer in Iudah, that without the breach of Gods lawe, could euer alter the externall forme of the iewiſh Church in the Leuitical prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood &amp; officers. And that the compariſon between the ſonne, and the ſeruant Chriſt and Moſes, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the externall, and not concerning the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gouernment of the inner man, as D. bridges ſayth it is plaine, bieauſe that Moſes had nothing to doe with the gouerning of the inner man, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were no prerogatiue for the Lorde to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred in faithfulnes before Moſes,<note n="b" place="margin">page 55. lin. 30.</note> in that thinge wherein Moſes neuer dealt. Nowe I aſſume that our fourme of Church-gouernement in Wales,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:181007:41"/>and this wicked booke, holdeth Ieſus Chriſt to haue ordained ſuch an externall forme of gouernment in his Church at his departure from earth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as at the pleaſure of the magiſtrate may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, without the brech of Gods inſtitution: which thing D. Bridges affirmeth page. 55. and all our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates will graunt that the magiſtrate may alter the forme of gouernement now eſtabliſhed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this gouernement, and this booke preferreth Moſes before Ieſus Chriſt. And I cannot ſee how far this differeth from blaſphemie. Now if Chriſt ſhuld be ſaide to haue ordained no externall regiment, then Moſes is far before him, and ſo the thirſt of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie in our prelates and their accompliſhes is turned into extreme drunkennes of impietie by this aſſertion.</p>
            <p>I beſeech the Lord in mercie to open your Hh. eies, that you may ſee how he and his people haue bene dealt with, by retaining ſuch lawes in force, as iuſtle and ouerthrow the royall prerogatiue of his ſonne. And the Lord make you to ſee whether thoſe men that defend the intereſt of the ſonne of God in this point, againſt the tyrannicall vſurpation of prelats, and haue brought for his title, vnaunſwerable eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, out of the ſacred records of Gods owne wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings (offending either in matter or circumſtance, in no one thing: but that they haue not dealt more earneſtly with your Hh. and more ronndly with the aduerſaries in the right of their maſter) haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be impriſoned, thruſt out of their liuings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled, railed vppon, and ſlaundered, (by vngodly and wicked prelates,) vnto your Hh. as ſeditious and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented men with the ciuill gouernment, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſubiects, and enemies to her Maieſties crowne. And ſurely the cauſe being made knowen vnto you
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:181007:42"/>as it is, howſoeuer the Lord may beare with your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight heretofore, in the ignorance of the waight thereof: yet if you do not now abrogate and aboliſh ſuch a Church gouernement wel may you hope for the fauour and entertainment of Moſes, that is, the curſe of the law, but the fauour and louing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Ieſus Chriſt, I doe not ſee how you ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer inioy.</p>
            <p>My ſecond reaſon. That forme of church-gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and booke or bookes, whiche maketh the ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall regiment, to bee an humane conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, ſuch a conſtitution, as is incluſiuely acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word, any more then the ciuill gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13. &amp; 2. Pet. 2.10.</note> alſo muſt be incluſiuely according to the word, and ſo may at the magiſtrates pleaſure be changed as the ciuill gouernment may, that gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that booke or bookes, (beſides that they prefer Moſes before Ieſus Chriſt as before) is a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked gouernment, and they wicked, ſophiſticall and vngodly bookes: But our gouernement in Churche cauſes, and<note n="b" place="margin">page. 55.</note> this booke with all other books of this greiſt, make the eccleſiaſticall gouernment to bee nothing elſe but an humaine conſtitution, whiche may bee altered at the magiſtrates pleaſure. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Church-gouernement in Wales, and this booke or bookes, are vngodly and wicked. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is prooued by theſe reaſons. Firſt becauſe they make no difference betweene that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the true worſhip of God, as eccleſiaſtical gouernement doth, &amp; that which appertaineth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ciuill pollicie.<note place="margin">2. Peter. 1.3.</note> Contrary to the Apoſtle who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in expres words, that we haue receiued by the knowledge of God, whatſoeuer belongeth vnto true religion, for ſo the word Euſebeia (tranſlated godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) ſignifieth in that place, wheras there was neuer
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:181007:42"/>yet any place of ſcripture found, wherin we are ſaid to haue by the knowledge of God, whatſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to anthropinen kteiſin, the ciuill magiſtrat called mans ordinance by the ſame apoſtle.<note n="a" place="margin">Peter. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe thinges which are inuented by them that neuer knew God, may be incluſiuelie according to the worde. Secondly Eccleſiaſticall gouernement being granted to be an humaine conſtitution, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Pope to haue ſufficient b warraunt out of the worde, not of his idolatrous and falſe religion,<note place="margin">And D. Bridges auoucheth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this for good doctrin as I will ſhew.</note> but of his ſuperioritie ouer ciuil magiſtrates, and al the Paſtors in the Churche. For why ſhould not hee (the ciuill magiſtrate granting him this ſuperioritie as they vnder his iuriſdiction do) be allowed by the word to be aboue the Emperour, and all other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and miniſters whoſoeuer, if the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call gouernement be an humane ordinance. For I am aſſured that the Emperor and all other princes in Europe may chuſe a magiſtrate ſuperiour vnto them all if they will. And why may not he be a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or an Arch-biſhop, if the Church-gouerment be an humane ordinance, or if it be lawful for either of them to be a Lord and be are ciuill office. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if Church-gouernment bee an humane conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then it may be lawful for a Church-gouernour to preach, adminiſter the ſacraments, ouerſee, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, &amp;c. and to be a king. For the Apoſtle maketh it lawfull for any ſupplying the place of an humane conſtitution lawfully, to bee a king, and I would they durſt denie it? And where then learned they that diuinitie, that it is more againſt the word, for a Biſhop to be Baſileus a king, Hyperichon a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, Hegamon a captaine or gouernour,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13. Luk. 22.25.</note> beeing titles ſanctified by the holy ghoſt for ciuill offices, then Curios a Lord, Hyperpheron a prelat of the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:181007:43"/>garter, Euergetes a lords grace. The former &amp; the latter being by our Sauiour himſelf forbidden vnto Biſhops or miniſters. The ſecond vz. Hyperpheron neuer read in the worde, that I can reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. If they ſay, that the abuſe of lordlines and graceleſſe grace, is forbidden by Chriſte; they haue bene anſwered, they are anſwered, and let them replie if they can, that the Lorde neuer allowed abuſe or tyrannie in ciuill gouernours, wheras he doth not forbid them to rule as Lordes, and to be called grace, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpeaketh of the ſanctified vſe of gouernement and titles: which ſanctified vſe lawfull in the ciuill magiſtrates, hee denieth to be lawfull in his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Becauſe therefore, firſt to make that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the outward worſhip of God, to haue no more ground out of the worde, then that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth vnto the ciuill magiſtracie. Secondly to allow of the Popes ſuperioritie, and to affirme that a miniſter may alſo be a king, are wicked and abſurd aſſertions, directly againſt the word as we ſee. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is wicked in like manner, to make the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall gouerment to be an humane conſtitution. And not vnlikly alſo by litle &amp; litle, as experience in poperie techeth vs, to paue the way for the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of the ciuill gouernment. For why may not a forged donation of Conſtantin, or Ludouicus Pius, in time ioyn the crown of England to the ſea of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, or Bangor eſpecially, which from Ioſeph of Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea can be prooued to haue a little better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuaunce of perſonall ſucceſſion, then Rome can from Peter, aſwell as it ioyned the kingdome of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia, the Dukedome of Naples the iſlands Corſica Sardinia, &amp;c. vnto the Popes miter?</p>
            <p>The thirde reaſon is thus ftamed (and I will be briefe) That forme of Church-gouernment &amp; that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:181007:43"/>booke or bookes, which teacheth that there is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be obſerued, beſides that, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion giuen by our ſauiour chriſt vnto his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Matth. 28.19.20</note> wherein they were enioyned to teach vs to obſerue whatſoeuer hee had commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, is a gouernement execrable and accurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, (and ſo are the bookes) by the ſpirite of God in plaine wordes. Gal. 1.9. And beeing ſuch, farre be it that either the gouernement or the bookes ſhoulde be maintained by law, ſuch a curſſe being pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the retaining of execrable things, as we find: Deut. 7.15. But our fourme of Church-gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Wales and this booke, with manye others publiſhed by auctoritie, teach the ſame. For where is it included, much leſſe, preſcribed in the woorde, that our ſauiour Chriſt abolliſhed an outwarde go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of the Church, in the Leuiticall pollity, being in no ſort an humaine ordinance, but altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſcribed by the Lorde him ſelfe, to the ende, that vnder the Goſpell, there ſhould be no gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but an humaine ordinaunce, that might bee chaunged at the pleaſure of man; Or where is it reuealed, that the apoſtles gaue the ciuil magiſtrat, when any ſhould be in the Church, the commiſſion to aboll ſhe the presbyterie eſtabliſhed by them, as our aduerſaries confeſſe, (as the b word ſaith by god himſelfe,<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5.12 Epheſ. 4.4. rom. 12.6. 1 pet. 4.10. Mat. 21.25. &amp; 12.11.</note> and therefore not to bee abrogated vntill his pleaſure in that point be known) becauſe there was no chriſtian magiſtrate. Therefore this gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and this booke or bookes are execrable and accurſſed.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that fourme of gouernement, and that booke or bookes, which affirme the kingdoome of Chriſt in the ourward gouernment to be a kingdom that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſhaken, that is altered or remoued as
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:181007:44"/>the ceremoniall gouernement was, affirme that which is contrarie to the expreſſe written worde of God, Heb. 12.28. and therefore not to be tollerated in anye chriſtian eſtate. But our Church gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Wales by L. bb. Arch-deacons, dumbe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, commiſſaries, &amp;c, in their making of miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, cenſures, excommunications, &amp;c, is ſuch, and ſuch is this vnlearned heape and ſophiſticall booke or bookes. Therefore both the gouernement and the booke or bookes affirme things contrary to the word, &amp; ſo are not to be tolerated vnleſſe we would haue the Lorde bring ſpeedye ſhame and confuſion vpon vs:<note place="margin">Pro. 26.2.7</note> for maintaining ſinne by law. The propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is moſt apparant; Becauſe that by the words (kingdome that cannot be ſhaken) muſt needes be ment perticularlye, whatſoeuer ſignification elſe they haue as more generall) the outward gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment receiued vnder the Goſpell ſince the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ceremoniall law, which being compared in regard of continuance, and remoouing, or doing away, which Moſes his gouernement, is ſaid to be a kingdom that cannot be ſhaken, that is, ſuch as the Lord neuer meaneth to alter again vnto the worlds end, as to haue another placed in the ſtead of it by him ſelfe, much leſſe by man, whereas that vnder Moſes<note n="a" place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note> is affirmed by Haggay, and here by the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to bee a kingdome or gouernment that can bee ſhaken or altered. And this is the proper meaning of the place. For by the worde kingdome, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſhaken, muſt needs be ment, either the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſaluation which we haue vnder the goſpel, or our enioying and poſſeſſing of eternall life, or els the outward gouernement, not onely in the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the worde, and adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but in the very church offices, the manner
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:181007:44"/>of their choice, and their ſubiects wherein they are occupied. But as concerning the aſſurance of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this life, and the poſſeſſion of eternall life in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which the fathers vnder the law had, it was no more to be ſhaken then ours, the meanes therevnto by the word preached, they had aſwell as wee, and ſo in theſe reſpects they had a kingdome that could no more be ſhaken then ours. It remaineth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that theirs was to be ſhaken, in regard of theyr outward gouernement, and therfore ours vnmoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this reſpect, which were ſenſeleſſe to be affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if Chriſt in his kingdome, wherevnto wee are heere ſubiects had inſtituted no externall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Can that bee vnmoouable which is not at al? more ſenſeleſſe it were to thinke this kingdome to be vnmutable, in regard of the ſacraments, and not of the perſons and offices, who were to deale with thoſe miſteries.</p>
            <p>To come againe to your Honors, you are not to learne, that to defend by lawe, or countenaunce by aucthority the breach of Gods ordinance, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of ſin, the defence of the ſin is hatred of God, who rewardeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their face that hate him, deu. 7.10. &amp; therfore alſo you are not to be taught, what horrible ſinnes you committee, in countenauncing and maintayning ſuch execrable impieties. They ar no trifles as you ſee. And I aſſure you, that Dathan and Abiram, the ſons of Eliab, men<note n="a" place="margin">Nom. 26 9.</note> famous in the congregation, had more colour of right to claime vnto them ſelues, either the ciuill gouernement from Moſes, or the prieſthoode from Aaron, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the ſonnes of Reuben the firſt born vnto whoſe lot<note n="b" place="margin">Geneſ. 49.4.</note> had he not defiled his fathers bed by all likelyhoode, either the ſcepter or the prieſthood ſhold haue fallen, then theſe vſurpers haue to claim
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:181007:45"/>the places they are in, whereunto either by right of inheritaunce according to the fleſh, or ordinaunce from God, they can lay no title. You are wiſe inough I hope to conſider, what it is to tollerate the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt breach of Gods law. Well if you be not carefull herof, yet at the leſt, look how you countenance the manifeſt ouerthrowe of her Maieſties ſepreame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and royall ſoueraigatie ouer her people, both miniſters and others which D. bridges as flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerthroweah in this booke, as euer did any that gaine-ſaied the ſame. For the proofe hereof, let his owne wordes bee brought foorth and arraigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before your Hh. page 448. line 3. theſe be his words. Doth S. Peter then forbid, that any one elder ſhould haue and exerciſe any ſuperiour gouernment ouer the cleargy, vnderſtanding the cleargie in this ſenſe. If hee doth not but alloweth it, and his ſelfe practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, then howſoeuer both the name, both of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning and of Cleargie may be abuſed, the matter is clear, that one prieſt or elder among the reſidew may hane, a lawfull ſuperiour aucthoritye ouer the cleargie, that is, ouer all the vniuerſall bodye of the Church in euerie perticular or ſeuerall congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Compare Bela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap. 10. lib 5. Con. 3. with this page, and you ſhall finde the one to haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken for the arch biſh. the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope.</note> and ſo not onely ouer the people, but alſo ouer the whole order of miniſters. Thus far are his words A ſhameles &amp; miſerable doctor he is, if he dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie them, but more miſerable and ſhameles, if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them he dare looke any chriſtian ſubiect in the face, much leſſe your Hh. Belarmine the chiefe popiſh writerin our daies, hath ſaid no more for the pope in fiue whole books written vpon this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie. Out of the D. words I thus reaſon. Whoſoeuer affirmeth that one prieſt amongſt the reſidue may haue a lawfull ſuperiour aucthoritie ouer the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall bodie of the Church, hee (beſides the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:181007:45"/>of a forrain power (affirmeth that a prieſt may exerciſe a lawfull ſuperiour authority ouer her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and all other magiſtrates, much more mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters within the vniuerſallbodie of the Church,<note place="margin">1. Eliza. 1 13. Elizab. 1.1. Elizab. 5</note> and ſo directly is within the compaſſe of treaſon, by the breach of the ſtatuts, prouided for the maintenance of her Maieſties ſupremacie within her owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. But D. Bridges doth this,<note place="margin">Doctorem ad capitale judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um voco poenae talionis me offe rens, niſi laeſa maieſtatis rerum prob auero mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ipſe ſibi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiterit. Ac deum teſtor me non patroni iugalum petere, ſed cauſa</note> let his own words witnes againſt him. Therfore he affirmeth that ſom one prieſt may exerciſe a lawfull ſuperiour authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer her Maieſtie, and ſo is within compaſſe of the ſaid ſtatutes, if he dare ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to that he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Nothing can be inferred out of his words, but that which is ſet downe in the propoſition, for I am ſure, he wil not be ſo impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly traiterous, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hir Maieſtie to be contained within the vniuerſal bodie of the Church. For by this meanes the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man would make her Maieſty to be an infidel, and ſo ſhould ſnare himſelfe againe within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of * treaſon. And if he ſaye, his meaning is not that this prieſt ſhould be a forainer,<note place="margin">13. Eliza. 1.</note> and ſo thinketh to delude the ſtatuts, the plaſter maketh the wound farre more grieuous and irkeſome. For firſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious indignitie is far greater vnto her right ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie, to make her owne vaſſall, to bee a ſuperiour gouernor ouer her, vnto whom no prince els in all Europe, will yeelde any homage, then to acknowledge her ſelfe to be within the ſheepefolde of a forraine Pope, who it may bee is a Noble man borne, and hath the Emperor, &amp; the greateſt ſtates in chriſtendome, vnder his paſtorall charge. In the ſeconde place, what notable contumelie is this for the noblekinges of Denmarke and Scots, the ſtate of Germanie, Heluetia and all others, that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected the Popes authoritie as vnlawfull, not onely
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:181007:46"/>in regard of his idolatrie and pride, but euen of his lordly rule and ſupreme dignitie, to holde it lawfull for them to haue an Engliſh prieſt to vſurpe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ouer them and the Churches within ther do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions? And I cannot expreſſe what indignitie it were to conceiue ſo vilely of her Maieſtie, the whol aſſemblie of parliament, and your Hh. as to deeme, that you baniſhed poperie out of the land no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then you thought it lawfull notwithſtanding, for an Engliſhe prieſte (I keepe the prieſtly D. owne wordes) in ſtead of an Italian pope to haue ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our aucthoritie ouer the vniuerſall bodie of the Church. And howſoeuer ſome lawyers not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding how the ſtate of the queſtion concerning the popes prerogatiue is ſet downe by the beſt late popiſh writers, might finde ſhifts for D Bridges, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the danger of the ſtatute, becauſe there is not a particular inſtance brought in by him of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular prieſt, and a particular prince: yet herof your Hh. may be aſſuredly perſwaded, that if the thinges ſet downe in this wretched and ſlaunderous booke, be tollerable &amp; canonical, the queſtion concerning the popes ſupremacie, (whiche is the point I vrge, and not the treaſon) is granted on the papiſtes ſide. For if it be yeelded, that one prieſt or elder among the reſidue, may haue a lawfull ſuperiour authority ouer the vniuerſall bodie of the Church, that an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle might be a biſh. affirmed by<note n="a" place="margin">page 272.</note> D. Bridges, that Peter was prince of the Apoſtles, being the title, &amp; as it were the iuibuſhe of<note n="b" place="margin">page 445. 446.</note> 2. pages, in this dutifull booke, that from Peter the originall of vnitie did ſpring, that the Church might be grounded vpon v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie (alledged by the D. out of<note n="c" place="margin">page 445.</note> Ciprian: The like ſentence beeing no leſſe then thriſe brought in by Bellarmine out of Ciprian alſo, to the ſame purpoſe:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:181007:46"/>if theſe things I ſay, be granted, what can the papiſts deſire more to inferr the popes ſupremacie? for ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will prooue Peters ſucceſſour to be this prieſt, or ſome other muſt be brought, that can ſhew better euidence then he can. This is Bellarmines own reaſon. De Rom. ponti. lib. 2. cap. 12. 753. D. and theſe be the points, in the proofe whereof hee hath ſweat and laboured ſo ſore, in his firſt two books, de Rom. pontif. And if the auoiding of a particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant would anſwere the ſtatute, no popiſh traitors hereafter will be gotten within the compaſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſeeing in generall tearmes they may lawfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch the popes ſupremacie, and ſtande vnto this high treaſon the particular opening wherof, would coſt them their liues, and they will ſay no more, but that one prieſt may haue a lawfull ſuperiour autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as D Bridges ſaith Peter had, ouer the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall bodie of the Church. Now whether this prieſte be the pope or no, or whether the pope may haue this ſuperioritie ouer her Maieſtie, as being within the bodie of the churche or no, they leaue it to the conſideration of others, the inſtance woulde bee as much as their life were worth. And what ſhold they endanger their liues by vttering that, in particular, which in generall belike may be affirmed with ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The generall aſſertion, that a prieſt may haue a lawfull ſuperior authoritie ouer the vniuerſall body of the church, being true and voide of treaſon: why ſhall not the particular inſtance that the pope may be this prieſt which may haue this ſuperiour autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ouer hir Maieſtie, as being included within the vniuerſall bodie of the church be ſo to? if one prieſt may haue this authoritie? what ſhall hinder whie the pope may not be this prieſt (though hee be not) his idolatrie he may leaue, his pride he may leaue,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:181007:47"/>his triple crowne he may leaue, his name of pope he may leaue, and whie then may not he ſomtimes, though not alwayes, be capable of this lawfull ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour authoritie,<note place="margin">Many of the Popes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues neuer ſat at Rome but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Lions, Arminia or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinion, looke Platina, Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Pantal. &amp;c.</note> as well as ſome other prieſt? yea, but this prieſt muſt not haue his ſcare at Rome. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he will remooue his chaire vnto Rauenna, or Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, and ſo there ſhalbe no difference between him and this prieſt wherof D. Bridges ſpeaketh. And by this good diuinitie, Sixtus the fifth, now pope of Rome, being no idolater, void of pride, abandoning his triple crowne, and name of pope, remoouing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his ſeate vnto LAMBETH, might bee that one prieſt, among the reſidue, that might haue a lawfull ſuperionr authoritie ouer the vniuerſall bodie of the church, as D. Bridges without bluſhing hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. Let him nowe go and barke at the godly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in this land, as he doth ſlaunderouſly in the preface of his prophane booke. The intentes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining the cinill gouernment, are found in the vndutifull casket of his own boſome, whereof their clothes are not once priuie. What ſhoulde I at this time lay open any more of his vndutifull poſitions? his booke I will at all times prooue to bee nothing els, but a popiſh quilt, let him challenge me of mine offer when he wil. This matter concerning her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſupremacie, being too too haynous of it ſelfe, I meane not to agrauate and make more odious. Your Hh. may ſee, how peſtilent and pernicious this wicked gouernment of our prelats is, euen vnto hir Maieſties ſupreame and ſuperiour authority, which neuer any ſincerelie ſeeking for reformation, at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time eyther denied or diminiſhed, the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly vnderſtood according to the meaning of the ſtatute. And whatſoeuer hee hath ſaide of the godly learned miniſters, you ſee that it is he &amp; his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:181007:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>fathers houſe, with the gouernment thereof, that go about to tread vnder foot the Lords annointed. And this is the good diuinity that this Balaam for his lucres ſake, is not aſhamed to teache, and your Hh. dread not to tollerate. As though we hadde to little to anſwere before the Lorde, for the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian dominion of the pope in this lande, hee muſt needs make a prieſt in the land which may fetch the plague from other nations to bee powred vppon vs. Rather then the madnes of ſuche a prophet ſhould be vnrebuked, the very dumbe aſſe, ſpeaking with a mans voice, would gain-ſay the fury of ſuch a phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtian tongue: I cannot thinke my Lordes, but that the Lorde hath ſome memorable plagues reſerued for you and vs vnder your gouernment, if notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all theſe things, you ſtil countenance ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Iſraell, as beeing the very ornaments of the Lords tabernacle.</p>
            <p>I haue ſet downe out of the infallible trueth of Gods eternall word, the reaſons whereby the holie ghoſt cutteth the throare, of all the corruptions in our church, and hath giuen a deaths wounde, vnto the vitall parts of this popiſh ware-houſe of Doctor bridges. And let me ſee who will dare to replie vpon them? As for D. bridges him ſelfe, his vnfauery and vnlearned ſtile, his popiſhe reaſons, long ſince ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of the ſchooles of all ſound deuines, hys tranflation of other mens writings, throughout hys whole booke, his vngodly and abhominable<note n="a" place="margin">Page 655.</note> praier that the preaching of the word may neuer bee had generally throughout the land, his ſcripture<note n="b" place="margin">Page 287.</note> being the ſubſcription of the ſecond epiſtle to<note n="c" place="margin">Page. 562.349.560.</note> Timothie, his alleadging of writers, as cleare againſt himſelfe, as blacke is to white, as of Auguſtine, Caluin, Areti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp;c, his<note n="d" place="margin">Page 44<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> imperfect periodes without ſence or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:181007:48"/>his<note n="a" place="margin">Page a 272.</note> Biſhop Iames, Arch-biſhops,<note n="b" place="margin">Page 259.69 266</note> Tim. and Titus, his tranſlations of<note n="c" place="margin">Page 450.</note> vos autem nolite vocari rabbi, into will not you bee called rabbi, with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other monumens of his prophane imprety, ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ignorance, and want of learning, euidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, that he was neuer as yet, in Platonis Politia, where any good learning grewe, but hath wallowed him ſelfe all his life, in Romuli fece, whence lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath ben long ſince banniſhed, &amp; godlines ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhone. And therfore he of al others can diſproue nothing: vnleſſe the queſtion before hand be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his ſide.<note place="margin">Yet let him know, that I wil either be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, or haue the cauſe granted at his hands.</note> For to omit, that in 160. ſheets of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he hath don nothing, but ouer thrown him ſelfe, vtterly ſhamed his whooriſhe cauſe, by ſhewing the nakednes thereof, tranſlated other mens writings, taught the reader howe to vnderſtand the learned diſcoarſe, and added marginall notes, ſo that if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men had neuer written, he would haue ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, this ſhalbe found vndoubtedly true through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole booke, that he hath made a couenant before hand, not to diſpute, vnleſſe you graunt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, &amp; all, and rather flatlie to be non plus then prooue any thing. But our 4. biſhops and their fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are, or would be accounted learned, I deſire no more againſt them al, but to be iudicially heard, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word, if I bee diſprooued in any one thing I haue written, I will not deſire to liue.</p>
            <p>Hence it muſt needs followe, (your Hh. hauing regard vnto the ſtate of your ſoules, and bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and your good name amongſt poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities) that if theſe things ſet downe bee true (if not bring vpon me deſerued ſhame &amp; puniſhment) you will either redreſſe the miſerable eſtate of diſtreſſed Wales, by erecting there a godly miniſtery, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing of al Cananitiſh reliques: or for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:181007:48"/>of a few vnconſcionable and godleſſe men, aduenture to vndergo the fiery and flaming execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the burning decree of Gods anger. My LI. be not deceiued, the Lord of heauen is angrie wyth you, and his whole<note n="a" place="margin">Ioſh. 7.9.21. ezech. 38.22.</note> hoaſt for the Babiloniſh gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe Achans. Retaine them no longer, if you woulde not fall before the enemie; When the Lorde ſhall plead with you, your wiues, children, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and the whole land, with peſtilence, or with blood, as he is likely to do, for theſe wadges of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable gold, it is not, the pontificall Lordſhips of by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, at whoſe commaundement, the lordes ſword will<note n="b" place="margin">Ierem. 47.6.</note> returne againe into his ſheath, when your gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſoules, ſhall cry for mercy at the Lords hands, it is not the proud, &amp; popelike Lordſhips of biſhops, their vſurped iuriſdictions, their prophane excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, their railing ſlaunders againſt Gods truth and his ſeruants, their blaſphemous breathing of the holye ghoſt vppon their Idol prieſts, that will driue the Lord to giue you and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. Let me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (though my perſon bee baſe, &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your Hh. that the iudgements of God againſt ſin, both in this life, and in the other of eternal woe and miſerie, may appeare ſo terrible in your eies, &amp; of that vndoubted conſequence, as you will no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger retaine vnder your gouernment theſe thynges, whoſe continuance doe giue the Lord iuſt cauſe in this life, to pronounce this, ſentence, by the mouth of<note n="c" place="margin">Iere. 22.29.30.</note> Ieremiah againſt euery one of you, and execute the ſame. O earth, earth, earth, heare the wordes of Iehouah, write theſe men deſtitude of children, men that ſhall not proſper in their daies, yea, there ſhall not be a man of their ſeed that ſhall proſper, and ſit at the counſell table, or beare rule in England anye more. And in the life to come, to ſaye: moreouer,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:181007:49"/>theſe<note n="a" place="margin">Luke. 29.27:</note> mine enemies that would not ſuffer mee to beare rule ouer them, and their people, bring hither and ſtay before my face, yea, binde them hand and foot, and throw them to vtter darknes, where there is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. And let me, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vppon my knees, with all ſubmiſſion, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, and more earneſt if it were poſſible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that my countrey-men by your meanes may haue the word preached, euen the meanes, wherby they may liue for euer with Abraham, Iſaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob in the kingdome of heauen. Graunt them this my Lords though I die for it. Oh I would thinke it an happie death, which ſhoulde make mee the firſt meſſenger to carie ſuch ioyful newes vnto the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note n="b" place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> Saincts, and aungels in heauen, as that Wales were conuerted from ſinne. And this the Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is the only ſcope of my writing, and not the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crediting, and galling of our lord-biſhops. Let not their places withſtand the ſaluation of my brethren, and the true ſeruice of God among them, and if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I either write, or ſpeak more againſt them, any further then their ſears are like to bee the ruine of her Maieſtie and your Hh. let it coſt mee my life. Heare me in this ſute, good my Lords, the rewarde whereof, your ſoules ſhall find, otherwiſe, I am like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to become a weariſome, and an importunate ſutor vnto you. The cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of that creature is as yet vnſeene, that ſhal enforce me (by the lords aſſiſtance to take a deniall at your hands.</p>
            <p>The cauſe is ſo iuſt, that if it were (as ſometimes it was by the<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 17.19.</note> Apoſtle himſelfe decided), in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians Areopago, a court for heathen iuſtice of famous and celebrated memorie, I doubt not but it ſhould be heard. And ſhall it not haue iuſtice at the chriſtian counſell table of England? Iuſtice my Ll. I ſay, for I ſeeke nothing els, but that the ſtatutes of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:181007:49"/>the God of iudgement &amp; iuſtice, may be made kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in my deare countrie, where now they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard off, Then the which, I knowe not what can be more iuſt, neither can I ſee what iuſtice in trueth, canne bee miniſtred by them that neglecte this cauſe. Verelye, for mine owne part (GOD ayding me) I will neuer leaue the ſuit, vntill I either obtain it at your hands; or bring the Lord in vengeance &amp; blood, to plead with you for repelling his own cauſe</p>
            <p>Here I know it will be anſwered, that counſellors can do nothing in the matter, her Maieſtie hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferted all vnto the prelates, in church cauſes. They haue dealt with her, they cannot, they may not be heard. Be it that her maieſtie hath bin mooued by you for the redreſſe of the church, you ſhuld do it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, &amp; againe, and neuer leaue vntill you be heard. Great matters are neuer brought to paſſe, without great &amp; mightie endeuours. Our ſinnes haue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſerued, then that the Lord ſhould at the firſt incline mercie vnto vs, in the ſight of her highnes. would any of you alter any part of the gouernment of his familie, being perſwaded by leude flatterers, that all were well, vnleſſe the abuſe were ſhewed, &amp; you earneſtly delt with for a reformation? And can you blame, that our ſoueraigne is hardly drawen to reforme the Church, whoſe eſtate euen in her hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, is ſaid daily out of the pulpit, to bee moſt flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, whereas the deformitie thereof is not made knowne vnto her? I knowe it is no ſmall perſwaſion that ſhould draw a Monarch, to alter and eſtabliſhe new lawes; vnles the vnanſwerable neceſſitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were made knowne vnto hir or him. Hir Maieſtie knoweth not (I ſpeake as I am perſwaded) the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting neceſſitie that lieth vpon her ſhouldrrs, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ning the Church. e She knoweth not the eſtate
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:181007:50"/>of her vntaught and damned ſubiects to bee as it is. Wherefore ſerue Counſellers, if her eies muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie where to ſee euerie thing? And what do your Hh. ſee, if you ſee not our caſe, and lament it? In this point I grant her eies ſhould be her owne chuſers: but if of ouerſight the waightieſt matters bee omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhould not you my Ll. put her in minde hereof, and in ſubmiſſion intreat her, yea and neuer leaue entreating, vntill ſhe yeeld, to turne away the wrath of God from her ſelfe and her kingdome, by aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing vngodly ordinances, and reſtoring beutie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which of you is he that hath, that doth, or wil performe this duetie to our Soueraigne? which of you will make knowne vnto her this which I haue written? I knowe I ſhalbe traducted, (and torne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in pieces with ſlaunders) as a ſeditious fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of newe attemptes, to ſtir vp her people to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation, at the leaſt, let me be made knowne vnto her by this name, that ſome way I may come to the triall of my cauſe in hand, and my warrantable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein. I am neither papiſt, Annabaptiſt, libertine, familian, one that dareth ſeperate himſelf from the godly aſſemblies in this lande, where the worde preached ſoundeth, nor yet one that holdeth any thing, either in ſubſtance or circumſtance con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the wholſome doctrine expreſſed or inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Gods reuealed word, of the old and new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: therefore let me haue the benefite of a Chriſtian, if not of a chriſtian ſubiect, not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned before my cauſe be hearde; whiche is not mine owne, but the cauſe of God his Churches, my countries and your Hh. I haue forged the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſlaunders that euer were coyned, or elſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of my country is moſt miſerable, and yours no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:181007:50"/>leſſe lamentable if it ſo continue. And if you make not the ſame known vnto her Maieſtie, &amp; labor not to amend it, the Lord make Queene Elizabeth and her crowne free from the blood of her deſtroyed people, and I pray God my Ll. their ſouls be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at your hands, and the Earle of Pembrokes, when you and hee ſhall not be able to anſwere for them. But it may be you will ay, that the worke is ſo difficult that it cannot poſſiblie be performed. Doe what lieth in you, and then the Lorde is aunſwered. The farther you wade herein, the eaſier will be the paſſage. Becauſe it is a worke of difficultie, therfore muſt you needes hinder the ſame by law, as you do in tollerating theſe abuſes? Becauſe the whol work is difficult, therefore ſhall it not be begon? Becauſe it is a hard matter to plant the ordinaunce of God, therefore muſt the breach thereof be in force and maintained? Becauſe in Canaan, the ſons of<note n="a" place="margin">Nom. 13.14.</note> Anak, and towns walled vp to heauen (mountains of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended excuſes) haue bin ſeene, therefore muſt you needes ſuffer the people brought by her Maieſtie, out of Egypt, to remaine ſtill in the wildernes, on this ſide lordan, euen vnder thoſe men, the dumbe miniſters, nonreſidents, L. Bb. I mean, who are fit for nothing, but to be captaines,<note n="b" place="margin">Nom. 14.4.</note> (whenſoeuer oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie ſhall ſerue) to bring them again into Egypt? Becauſe our land by reaſon of our continuaunce in ſinne, and that we haue not had skilfull workemen among vs, doth not nowe bring forth religion and godlines in the meaſure it ſhoulde, therefore muſt you needs be ſure, that prophanenes and Atheiſm ſhalbe ſowne, and the breach of Gods law flowriſhe there in the perſons of theſe men. Therfore the iuſt Lord will be iuſt, in<note n="c" place="margin">Read Ezek. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Zeph. 3.3.</note> the middeſt of you, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he reckoneth for theſe things, becauſe you are
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:181007:51"/>ſo far from doing what you may, in the planting of godlines, that you ſuffer impietie againſt his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to bear ſway, and that by law &amp; autoritie? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hardnes of the worke, this I make kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en vnto you, that if you wilbe ruled by the canon of the word, you ſhalbe abl with eaſ, &amp; the good liking of your people, to do ſo much therin, as you ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer your owne liues from the heauie wrath of God. But if that rule ſhall not take place, anye far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then it may ſtand with the countenance of L. biſh. and other corruptions of the Eccleſiaſticall ſtate (for as concerning the ciuill gouernment, the Lorde knoweth howe farre I am from dealing with it) I ſee not what you can ſay vnto the Lorde, when he hath made you and your people, an aſtoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and an hiſſing vnto all the nations vnder heauen: but<note n="a" place="margin">Nehem. 9.39.</note> ſurelie thou art iuſt in all that is come vpon vs, for we would not be ruled by thy word.</p>
            <p>Well, the word teacheth and requireth 2. things, and no more of you in this worke. In both it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth your obedience if you would be directed by it. Firſt, it requireth that Wales may be redreſſed, by proclaiming that commiſſion giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt vnto his Apoſtles in euery corner thereof,<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> &amp; both the parts of the commiſſion, it requireth to be kept inuiolable, as well that, of go preach &amp; baptize as the other, of teach them to obſerue whotſoeuer I haue commanded you. Secondly, while you ſtay the Lords leaſure, to raiſe vp fit men for this worke in euery congregation, it requireth that the people where preachers cannot be placed at the firſt, may haue ſome ſtay, that inconueniences bee auoyded. For the Lord will not haue religion ſo vndiſcreetly eſtabliſhed, as that inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences (as much as may be) be not wiſely preuented. In effecting hereof, two
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:181007:51"/>things are to be looked vnto, both of them greatly furthering the worke. Firſt the bleſſing of God is to be laboured for, by humbling your ſelues and your people, with Daniel before the Lord,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.1.3.</note> in faſting and prayer, and then you ſhall ſee, he will be with your endeuours. Secondly, you muſt enioyne euery man according vnto his place, to haue a hande in this worke, and encourage the gentlemen, and people that ſhalbe found forward, by gracing and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing them for their forwardnes in religion, and ſhewing that the more forward they bee, the more credit they are like to purchaſe with your Hh. And you muſt not ſuffer an vncircumciſed mouth to bring<note n="a" place="margin">Nomb. 14.36</note> a ſlander vppon that good lande whereunto the Lorde offereth to bring you and your people, if you would obey, much leſſe to lift vp a<note n="b" place="margin">Nom. 14.10.</note> ſton againſt Caleb or Ioſhuah, that withſtande the furie of a who I wicked hoaſt in the Lords defence. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if you ſuffer all to ſit ſtill, and looke vppon our deſolations; the moſt to liue on the ſweetnes of our ruines, and diſcountenance all that labour therein: you can looke for nothing elſe ſhortly, but this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable complaint, and it is a great work of God, that we haue not hard the ſame long ago, of euery profeſſor in this land. Whither ſhal<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 1.18.</note> we go? our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and their harde entertainment hane diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged our hearts: would ro<note n="d" place="margin">Nom. 14.2.4.</note> God that we had died in the land of Egypt, would to God wee were dead: were it not better for vs to turne into Egypt? come let vs make a captain, and returne thither. The land in deed is a good land, whereunto when our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne brought vs out of Egypt, wee entended to make our iourney: but alaſſe, we are neuer able to ſtand againſt the pouertie, loſſes, impriſonment, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance by our ſuperionrs; that our brethren
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:181007:52"/>haue ſuſtained, which haue ſet their faces towards this land, neuer able to ſwalow vp the ſlanders, and bitter names of Puritanes, preciſians, traitors, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious libellers, that we ſee, raiſed againſt thoſe that would bring vs thither. And therfore my Ll. in vain ſhal you vſe other means, &amp; leaue this vnattemted.</p>
            <p>The redreſſe of Wales conſiſteth of two partes both muſt bee ſpeedily ſet vppon by your Hh. or elſe certainly the iudgements of God wil finde you out. Firſt you muſt aboliſh out of the Churche, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you finde to be a breach of Gods ordinance (as I haue proued dumb miniſters, nonreſidents, &amp; 1. biſh. to be) or els your reformation will be little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then that of the<note n="a" place="margin">2. King. 17.33.</note> Samaritans, who feared Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah, but worſhipped their owne gods. Secondly you muſt place as many godly learned, as can be found, to call the people, and ſee them prouided for. If the complaint be made for want of ſufficient men, and ſufficient ſtale for their liuings: for the men, take al thoſe whom the lord hath made fit for this work, &amp; hee can require no more at your handes vntill hee raiſe more, which if he neuer doe, your good ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors and encouragements vnto ſtudents &amp; others, not being wanting to bring this to paſſe, he cannot in iuſtice puniſhe you, though your people bee not taught. Bicauſe you haue ſeene al thoſe wel beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whom he quallified for that calling, &amp; ſo do now expect a bleſſing from him vpon your labours, that you might ſend more. The ſubterfudge will be, but the couert of a net, to aske (as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly our prelats do) how there ſhoulde be poſſiblie founde, as many learned men as Wales requireth, ſeeing they who are founde, are not placed there. And doe you deale well with the lord, that be cauſe al canot be brought at once to ſerue him, as hee willeth, therefore they
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:181007:52"/>that may ſhall not? The ſame is to bee ſaide of the miniſters liuings. Remoue the dumb miniſters, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the L. bb. (if you will not do this, you go beſide the word of God, &amp; ſo there is no direction for you) and there will be mo liuings void, able to maintain godly miniſters, then ſhalbe, I feare me, good men found to ſupplie the places. And verely, I maruaile what men perſuade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, the Lord to be, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they thinke hee can be ſatisfied with ſuche ſielie ſhifts? is it not a ſtrange matter, to finde Church li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings in Wales for L. bb. nonreſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; idoles, to ſin againſt God, and ſtarue ſoules withal, and deny any to be there, for godly miniſters do honor God, and work the ſaluation of his people. The children muſt ſtarue for want of breade, becauſe the dogs before their eies muſt be fed therewith. Good reaſon? yea, but the remouing of thoſe men, would be likelie to ſet the land on fire. Marke how ſutile the deuil is, in the maintenance of his kingdome. When godly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are deprined, becauſe they will not link the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with wicked B. b to betraie the kingdonm of Chriſt, and ouerthrow the lawes of this land, there is no inconuenience ſered. But if ſatans meſſengers be once ſhoued at: behold, the land wil not be able to beare this loſſe. I grant in deede my Ll. that men which make no conſcience for gaine ſake, to break the law of the eternal, and maſſaker ſoules (as theſe do) are dangerous ſubiectes, and not to be truſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further, then they are fed.</p>
            <p>The ſtay therefore muſt be either in regarde of theſe men, or the common people. Theſe men are of 2. ſorts, ſome few haue gifts for the miniſtery, thoſe would be imploied that way, and compelled to bee faithfull. The moſt of them are vnſauerie ſalt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding far be it that they and their families,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:181007:53"/>ſhould be turned vnto the wide world to ſeeke their liuings, and therefore ſome part of that which now they poſſeſſe with ſacriledge, beſtowed vpon them, being out of the miniſterie, they might enioy with a good conſcience. And a ſmall thing this way allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them, woulde be bleſſed, wheras whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer now they poſſeſſe is execrable. For the people, the ſtay for them is, eyther in regard of the publike meetings on the Sabboth, or the ſacraments, mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and burial. For the keeping of the Sabboth. The word requireth they ſhould, if poſſibly they can, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorte where preaching is, vntill good miniſters bee placed in euery parriſh. If the places be too farre, as commonly our parriſhes be very large, and it is not likely in ſhort time to plant preachers, ſo neere to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as the people may euery Sabboth reſort to them, they muſt be enioyned to meete togither in their pariſhe churches, &amp; ſome diſcreet man from among themſelues appointed to read the word, and vſe ſom forme of praiers as ſhalbe thought meeteſt by the aduiſe of the godly learned. Concerning the ſacraments, the word requireth they ſhould reſort vnto a preaching miniſter for them,<note place="margin">There is adulter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ie amongſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fidels, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a miniſter is not eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required in Matrimonle. Ruth 4.10.11.</note> &amp; not attempt to keepe their children vnbaptized any longer then they muſt of neceſſitie. Marriage is moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to be done by the miniſter. But it is no proper eſſentiall worke of the <hi rend="sup">a</hi> miniſter, and therfore may be ſolemniſed by others, at the magiſtrats appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Concerning buriall, it is a worke of chriſtian charitie, and being the laſt dutie that we are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme towards the departed, we ought to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie them decently, and orderly, with all comlineſſe vnto the graue. The word mentioneth or includeth no forme of prayers vſed at burials, therefore they ar ſuperfluous, nether is the miniſter as in an actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:181007:53"/>belonginge to his office, to haue any more to doe herein, then any other of the brethren</p>
            <p>Thus haue I ſet downe vnto your Hh. the onelye courſe in regard of ſubſtance, that the word waran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to bee taken in ſuch a deformed eſtate, as ours is. And now my Ll. let my counſell bee acceptable vnto you,<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 4.24.</note> breake off your ſinnes, by rooting out theſe plants, which the Lord neuer planted in hys vineyard, and your iniquities by adoring the ſame, as much as in you lyeth, ſo there may be an healing of your former ouer-ſight. If not, the lords face will be againſt you, yours, and the whole land for euill and not for good. O my Ll. is it not a miſerable caſe, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold ſo liue vnder your gouerment in this life, as they canot poſſibly but liue in hel in the life to come. O my Ll. heaen cannot be obtained when we are gone; Oh my Ll. now is the time for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell to flowriſh in Wales or neuer; Oh my Ll. if her Maieſtie, and your Hh. (whome from my very heart I wiſh the Lord to bleſſe) ſhould be gone the way of all the world, for mine owne part, the very ſtaffe of my hope, to ſee any good doone amongeſt my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſhould be broken. Blame me not therefore, if I deale earneſtly in a cauſe of ſo great a moment, and ſo vnlikely to be obtained of our wofull poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whome my ſuit in a moſt nere ſort concerneth. Oh whye ſhould they haue cauſe to ſaye, the Lorde bee iudge betweene vs, and the gouernours, whiche were vnder Queene Elizabeth in the daies of our fathers, for they might haue opened our eies, and healed our wounds, which now, (alaſſe) are deſperat and paſt recouerie.</p>
            <p>It is now ful 29. yeares and vpward, ſince Babilon hath bin ouerthrown in Wales, rather by the voice of hir Maieſties good lawes, (whome good Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:181007:54"/>not for this woorke) then by the ſound of anye trumpet, from the mouthes of the ſons of Aaron a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. But alaſſe, what ſhall we and our poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be the better for this, if Syon bee not built. And what comfort can Zerubabell or nehemiah haue to bring a people out of Babilon, if they meane but to reaedifie Sbilo, ſeeing it is the beautie of Syon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord delighteth. Wee haue cauſe indeede to thanke God, that this wicked eitie hath bene by hir Maieſtie in ſome ſort broken downer but we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the better, ſeeing the walls of Sion lie euen with the ground. Nowe for the ſpace 28. yeares, no man greatly labored to hir maieſty, the Parliament, your Hh. or to the people themſelues, either by ſpeaking or writing in the behalfe of either of theſe vnrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable eities. Men belike thinking no more to bee required at their hands, then the razng of Babell, &amp; the deuil as yet contenting himſelf with Bethel. The laſt yeare, as I am almoſt peſuaded, the verye ſame day, or by all likly-hood the very ſame week: vpon a ſuddain, the enterpriſes of the building of both, in 2. ſeueral books, iſſuing from two of the remoteſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in our lande (South-wales, and North-wales) was taken in hand. The one of the bookes pleading the cauſe of Sion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming forch priuiledged by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authority, &amp; alowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, was directed vnto hir ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty &amp; the Parliament, requiring at their hands, by vertue of the lords own mandatory letters, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this work, ſhewing by euidence of gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt antiquity, this to bee required of duety at their handes, as a part of the homage due vnto his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whoſe feudaries and vaſſalles, all the princes &amp; ſtates vnder heauen muſt acknowledge themſelues to be, &amp; a portion of that inheritance, beeing theirs by liniall diſcent from their predeceſſors, the godly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:181007:54"/>kings and rulers, who time out of mind, alwaies lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their ſhulders vnto this burthen. The other writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Welch, printed in an obſcure caue in North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wales, publiſhed by an author vnknown,<note place="margin">Y druch Chriſt. anogaw.</note> &amp; more vn learned, (for I thinke hee had neuer read any thing, but the common publiſhed reſolution of R. P. a book containing many ſubſtantiall errors, frier Ruſh, and other ſhamefull fables) ſtood to by none, &amp; hauinge no reaſons to ſhew why his Babilon ſhould be reae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified, it contained it ſelfe within the handes of a few ſimple priuate men and neuer durſt vnto thys hour, be made known vnto your Hh. Both the books in this thing had the ſame ſucceſſe, in that both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither they fel into the hands of the prelats, who as they pretend are enemies vnto both places, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly vnto Syon, eſpecially, as it appeared by their harde dealing with the pation of that cauſe, whereas the fautors of the other, were either not at all dealt with, or very curteouſly entertained of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The reaſon of their enmitie vnto both: but their ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred vnto Syon, is, that neuer I feare me, meaning to go thither,<note place="margin">This is ſpoken in regard of the Church-gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> and conſtrained by law to be enemies vnto the other, they haue of the golde of Caldea, &amp; the droſſe of Ieruſalem compacted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a citie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they meane to content themſelues, vntill they returne vnto Babel againe, or (the Lord be merciful vnto them) vnto a worſe place. Haue they not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good cauſe to be the more beholding vnto the one for the golde, then to the other for the droſſe? Well my Ll. bee you aſſured hereof, that they who ſtirred vp both theſe inſtruments both at one time, wil neuer ſuffer them to ceaſe, vntil in Wales, either a church of Chriſt, or a ſynagogue of ſatan be built. Out of queſtion, the concurring of both cauſes ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Lorde hath ſome ſecreat worke in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:181007:55"/>matter. Satans inſtruments for their parts, were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer buſier, ſince hir Maieſties raigne, then they are at this hower, and ſhall be ſtil? they trecherouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawes of God and this land, ſeek to bring the people again vnto AEgypt. I acording vnto both dutifully endeuour, neuer to let them reſt, vntill it pleaſe God, by hir Maieſtie and your Hh. to bring them within the lande of promiſe, no though they were vppon mounte Nebo, whence with their eies they might view the ſame. They haue dealt, &amp; deale ſecretly with poore ſoules in darke corners, &amp; dare not make known their fabulous cauſe. I haue dealt all this while, in the face of the ſun, and now before your Hh. I want not a good cauſe, and by the grace of God, it ſhall not want a defender, or hide the face as long as I liue. Whether you countenaunce it or no, I know it ſhal one day preuaile, when this wil be the Lord knoweth beſt: but the matter is, whether you wil imbrace chriſt in the building of his church or ſathan in continuing the breaches thereof. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Ll. entertaine THIS CAVSE, and you giue ſatan the foile, reiect this, and you ſtreng then him. And trie, if you denye it the hearing, whether the very papiſts in this land, will not be thereby encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to ſupplicate vnto your Hh. that you woulde grant them the liberty of their ſeared conſciences, to commit publike idolatrie.</p>
            <p>Al that hitherto I haue ſpoken, I haue ſpoken, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the cauſe of chriſt, which is a good cauſe, or in the cauſe of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If I ſeek the building of his ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagog, wil you let me liue? if of the church of chriſt, wil you denie me your helpe? which yet againe, and againe in the name of the eternall God, I require &amp; for the pretious death &amp; paſſions ſake of Ieſus chriſt I earneſtly deſire at your hands. My Ll. as you wold
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:181007:55"/>haue the Lorde to entertaine your ſoules in the life to come, as you would haue him ſhew you any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as you loue her Maieſtie &amp; hir life, as you would haue the continuance of her raigne ouer vs, which the lord vndoubtedly thretneth to ſhorten, becauſe he would bring ruine vpon you &amp; vs all, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his trueth, as you woulde not haue your names razed from vnder heauen, as you would not haue the Lord to bring vpon vs the Spaniſh, Italian Romiſh, or Guiſian forces, as you woulde not haue thoſe, who ſhall liue to ſee the deſolation and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſorrowe, which the Lorde is to bring vpon this lande, not abide to ſee, you, and your children ryde or go in the ſtreets, as you would not haue the moſt contemptible to ſtretche forth his hande vpon the deareſt things you poſſeſſe, &amp; offer violence before your eies, vnto the fruit of your bodies: ſo entertain this cauſe, graunt this ſuite, and haue a care of the Lords true ſeruice, in Wales: etherwiſe I feare me, the vengeance of God will neuer leaue you &amp; your poſterities, as long as there is a man of your houſes vnder heauen. And notwithſtanding the caſe of the Earle of Pembroke is neuer the better, if he ſtil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to beare rule within theſe gates, where the Lords Sabboths are not ſanctified.</p>
            <p>Ezekiel in deede is not now liuing, to put you in minde of the neceſſitie of redreſſing of thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, by laying open the corruptions of all eſtates vnder your gouernement, as he doeth, cap. 22, of his propheſie. His words I will ſet downe, that your Hh. may waye our eſtate with the time wherin the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet liued, and ſee whether the Lord will ſpare you and vs, if we ſtill prouoke him to ſmite. There is a conſpiracie of her prophets in the middeſt thereof,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.25.26.27.28.29.</note> faith the prophet, like a roaring lyon, rauening the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:181007:56"/>pray, they haue deuoured foules: they haue taken the riches and precious things: they haue made hir manie widowes in the midſt therof: hir prieſts haue broken my law, and haue defiled mine holy things: they haue put no difference betweene the holy &amp; prophane, neither diſcerned between the vncleane and the cleane, and haue hidd their eies from my Saboth, and I am prophaned among them. Hir prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the midſt thereof are like wolues, rauening the prey, to ſhed blood, &amp; to deſtroy ſoules for their owne couetous lucre. And her I rophets haue daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with vntempered morter, ſeing vanities, &amp; diuining hes vnto them, ſaying: thus ſaith the Lord Iehouah, when Iehouah hath not ſpoken. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the land haue violently oppreſſed by ſpoiling and robbing, and haue vexed the poore and needy: yea, they haue oppreſſed the ſtranger againſt right. Thus far Ezekiel. Be the ſinnes of our prophets, of our princes, &amp; of our people the ſame, that heare he ſpeketh againſt, be they greater, or be they leſſe: yet without controuerſie,<note place="margin">Verſe. 30</note> if the Lorde may ſaye, I haue ſought for a man among the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellors of England, thatſhuld make vp the hedge, &amp; ſtand in the gap be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me for the land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it, but I found none: then wo be vnto vs, for that ſhal fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which is ſet downe in the prophet. Therefore haue I powted out mine indignation vpon them,<note place="margin">Verſe. 31</note> &amp; conſumed them with the fire of my wrath: their owne waies haue I rendred vpon their heads, ſaieth the Lord Iehouah. And vnleſſe there were iuſt cauſe to think that this Lord had either already, or ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ment to pronounce this ſentence againſt vs, wee might contemne &amp; ſcorne at the carped aſſaults of the Spanyards, or any other the enemies of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and her Maieſties whoſoeuer. But as long as we
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:181007:56"/>giue not the right hande vnto the Lorde by entring into his ſanctuarie, we haue iuſt cauſe to feare a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is no nation, much more a people in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as the ſand, which is by the ſea ſhore. Our leags and moſt ſtable couenants with the enemies the lord will ſoone diſanull, ſtanding thus at the ſtaffes end with his maieſtie as we do. And as<note n="a" place="margin">Ierem. 37.</note> Ieremie ſaid vnto the king, and ſtates in his time: though we had ſmitten the whole hoaſt of the Spanyardes (that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend our ouerthrow) &amp; there remained bur woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded men among them: yet ſhould euerie man riſe vp in his tent, and ouerrun this lande. Let vs looke aſſuredlie, whenſoeuer the abiecte and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemie ſhall aſſaile vs, abiect and contemptible I ſaie, in all reſpects in compariſon of the value and ſtrength of our men and munition (and the lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them a thouſand folde more) that this God whoſe ſeruice is ſo little eſteemed of vs, will ſend a terror into the harts of our valianteſt, and ſtouteſt men: ſo that he, whoſe heart is as the heart of a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall become as weake as water: and one ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie ſhal chaſe a thouſand of vs, becauſe the hand of the lord will be againſt vs for our ſinnes. It is not therefore the Spaniſhe furniture and preparations: but the ſinnes within the land, that we are moſt of all to feare. For although the armie of the Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde were conſumed with the arrowes of famine: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the contagious, and deuouring peſtilence had eaten them vp by thouſands: although their tottering ſhippes were diſperſed and carried away with the whirle-winde and tempeſt: although mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; aſtoniſhment were amongſt them, from him that ſitteth in the throne, vnto her that grindeth in the mil: although the lords reuenging ſword in the hand of the ſauage Turke had ſo preuailed againſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:181007:57"/>them, as it had left none in that vncircumciſed hoſt, but languiſhing and foyled men, notwithſtandinge a conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible &amp; withered remnant of the plague &amp; famine: a nauie of winde and weather-ſhaken ſhips: a refuſe of feeble and diſcomfited men, ſhalbe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently able to preuaile againſt this land, vnleſſe an other courſe be taken for Gods glory in Wales by your Hh. then hitherto hath bene.</p>
            <p>If I did ſpeake vnto infidels and vngodly atheiſts, I know I ſhould not be ſo plaine, becauſe vnto ſuch the trueth is at ſometimes vnſeaſonably ſpoken. But I ſpeake vnto your Hh. that haue vndertaken the profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, and therefore ſhoulde be at all times fit to heare the trueth of your God. And I know no temporizing trueth, no temporiſing iudgements of God againſt ſinne, no trueth that is to be concealed vnto Chriſtians, becauſe their Hh. cannot brooke the ſame, no trueth my LL that is, either not at all, or minſinglye not to bee vttered, becauſe ſtates loue not to heare thereof. So that I was in this matter, not to conſider what your high places were content to hear but what was the dutie of your high places to heare. And therefore I ſhould thinke it, I proteſt an vndutifull and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring petition, to intreat your Hh. not to be offended with me, for vttering the trueth. As though I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed you woulde thinke it wonderfull that a man ſhould aduenture to ſpeake euen in the cauſe of his GOD, anye farther then ſtood with your good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p>I know the infirmities &amp; wants of men that deal in good cauſes, are commonly beaten vpon the bak of the cauſe they handle. Therefore the Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how carefull I haue beene to keepe it vnſpotted, and my ſelfe out of all vnneceſſary daunger. Setting
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:181007:57"/>downe nothing before I had weighed what might enſue, either in regard of the mater, or maner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery. This I am aſſured, that in the whole woorke, there is nothing whereby any law of the land canne take holde of me. But why did I publiſh a matter of ſuche waight, before I acquainted your Hh. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with? Grant the pitition, &amp; I will redeeme mine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſight heerein, (if it can be prooued any, which I know to be none) with the loſſe of my life: if you do not meane to yeeld vnto it, neither would you haue done it being mooued thervnto by priuate writing. The cauſe I make known; to the end it may be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and herein let not my life be precious vnto me, vpon the neceſſity of the publiſhing thereof I ſtand: bicauſe that the world maye ſee, when you redreſſe thoſe things, that you did nothing, which you durſt leaue vndone, vnleſſe you would haue brought ſwift deſtruction vpon your ſelues, and the whole lande. But what folly is it to think, that ſuch great matters in our daies wil be reformed? Rather what iniury do they to your Hh. that thinke you will countenance any longer the breache of Gods lawes. And in this point let the good opinion, that they which aleadge ſuch pretences conceiue, be weighed with my duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſwaſions of your Hh. and both our cauſes iudged accordingly. For mine own part, I thinke the maieſty of the cauſe to be ſuch, as they who are the lords, dare not but entertaine it, &amp; tremble to think that all this while it hath bene ſo careleſly attended vpon. And it is in the behalf therof, that I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to deale with you, who other-wiſe durſt not haue ſuffered my voice to be hard in the ears of the rulers of my people. Let what I haue written be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, yea by mine aduerſaries them ſelues, (if I haue anye) and it ſhall appeare that I haue made a
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:181007:58"/>conſcience how I haue dealt with my ſuperiours, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thoſe concerning whome it is ſaid, you are gods, leaſt I ſhould ſeeme to leaue behinde mee the leaſt print, of a minde in anye ſorte tending to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame them or their gouernment. As I haue beene carefull herof: ſo let the Lord, yea and no otherwiſe, (which I ſpeake as far as my corruptions do permit) graunt this cauſe and my ſelfe alſo if it be his wil, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in your eies. Indeede in regarde of the cauſe I commandatory wiſe vnto your Hh. but in regard of my ſelfe, I come in feare and trembling, as vnto the lords vice-gerents, entreating moſt humbly, that the dignitie of ſo worthy a cauſe be thought off, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the more diſhonorably: becauſe it is brought in my hands. And I proteſt, in reſpect of my ſinnes, that the Lord may iuſtly denie it the fauor it deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in your eies, bicauſe I am a dealer therein. But this ſhould be no cauſe why your Hh. ſhould giue it a repulſe. For in the eies and ears of al the world I make it known, that it is the cauſe of the liuing god, wherein I deale, and that if it had beene poſſible for me to haue written more humbly &amp; dutifully, I had done it. Or if I had ſeene any way, that might haue bene likelier to preuail with my ſuperiors then this courſe: I take the Lord to record vnto my ſoul, that I would not haue vſed this. And I would to GOD I could tell how to make the cauſe plaucible. So far I am from ſetting down any thing, that might carrie with it any ſhew of occaſion to hinder and diſgrace the ſame. Well, I haue done my endeuour: the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe I expect at the lords hands, vnto whom I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the cauſe, and the ſaluation of that pore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>The ſworde of iuſtice (reached vnto you by the Lord himſelfe, to take puniſhment of him only that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:181007:58"/>is an<note n="a" place="margin">Rom 13.4.</note> euil doer, I fear not: becauſe I haue not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. If it ſhould be drawn againſt me, for this action the preſident wold be ſuch as they, who ment here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to propheſie vnto your Hh. might be aduiſedly counſelled,<note n="b" place="margin">Micha. 2.6.</note> not to prophiſie, &amp; the Lord as a token of your iuſt deſtruction to enſue, would ſay they ſhal not propheſie nor take ſhame. If I haue ſpoken any vntruth, beare witneſſe thereof, if a truth, I dare by the lords aſſiſtance ſtand to it, and demand what he is, that wil preſume to obiect, and throw himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vengeance of God, by puniſhing me an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent? The Lord may for my other ſinnes, bring mine head vnto the graue with bloud: but in this cauſe, what haue I offended? and therfore vndoubted woe will betide him that ſhall moleſt me for this worke, Howſoeuer it be, thus I haue performed a dutye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Lorde, and his church, my countrey and your Hh. which I would doe if it were to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, though I were ſure to endanger my life for it. And be it known. that I am not afraid of earth in this cauſe. And if I periſh, I periſhe, my comfort is that I know whether to go, and in that day, wherin the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creats of all hearts ſhabe manifeſted, the ſinceritie of my cauſe alſo ſhall appeare. It is enough for mee that howſoeuer I be miſerable in regard of my ſins, yet vnto Chriſt, I both liue and die, and purpoſe by his grace, if my life ſhould be prloonged to liue her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, not vnto my ſelf, but vnto him &amp; to his church, otherwiſe then hithertoo I haue doone. The Lorde is able to raiſe vp thoſe that are of purer hands and lippes then I am to ſpeake and write in the cauſe of his honor in Wales, &amp; the Lord make them, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they ſhalbe neuer to be wanting vnto ſo good a cauſe, the which becauſe it may be the Lordes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I ſhall leaue them behinde me in the worlde, I
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:181007:59"/>earneſtly and vehemently commende vnto them as by this my will and teſtament: And haue you pore Wales in remembraunce, good my Lordes, by eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the word preached there, that the bleſſing of many a ſaued ſoule therein, may follow her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and your Hh. ouertake you, light vpon you, and ſticke vnto you for euer. The eternall God giue hir Maieſtye and your Hh. the honour of building hys church in Wales, multiply the daies of hir peace o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, bleſſe hir and you, ſo in this life, that in the life to come the inheritance of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen may be hir and your portion. ſo be it good Lord.</p>
            <p>Were my dutifull heart towards your Hh. throughly knowen, then I doubt not, but I ſhould bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowen vnto you then by my name.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN PENRI.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>Maſter D. SOMES booke was publiſhed this day, I haue read it. The man I reuerence from my heart as a godly and learned man. The reaſons he vſeth againſt me, in the queſtions of the reading miniſtrie, and communicating with them, I had aunſwered as you may ſee in this booke before he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. They are faultie, either becauſe they deſire that for graunted which is the queſtion, or make thoſe things of like nature, wherein there is a great diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, as the arguments drawen from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie and the Leuiticall Prieſthood. I haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The cauſe, &amp; the reuerence I owe vnto the man, though the reaſons he vſeth, deſerue not to be twiſe read ouer) will enforce me to anſwere him at large. There be certaine faults eſcaped in the print, beare with them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:181007:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
